<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linux by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/linux/</link><description/><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 21:01:49 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/linux/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I broke my Arch System</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/dev/i-broke-my-arch/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/dev/i-broke-my-arch/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Today, I updated my system running Arch Linux after a month using <code>pacman -Syu</code>. I rebooted my system to find a black screen instead of the SDDM login screen. I tried pressing the Caps Lock key, and I could see its light toggle. This meant that things were not that bad.</p>
<p>I changed the tty using <kbd>Ctrl</kbd> + <kbd>Alt</kbd> + <kbd>F2</kbd> and logged in to my system. I tried downgrading the Linux kernel but that didn&rsquo;t help. I tried disabling the optimus-manager and sddm services, and tried starting the Xorg server using <code>startx</code> or <code>xinit</code>. None of this worked.</p>
<p>The fix was to rebuild the optimus-manager package. It turns out that Python was upgraded from 3.9 to 3.10 in the update, and this broke Optimus Manager. I rebuilt it, and I am able to access the login screen and my window manager again.</p>
<p>I could see that some of my AUR packages were still built using older versions of Python using this command:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#e7e9db;background-color:#2f1e2e;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">pacman -Qoq /usr/lib/python3.9
</code></pre></div><p>I rebuilt all those packages to use the latest Python version.
I also finally installed <code>yay</code> to manage all my AUR packages.</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>