<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Reviews by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/reviews/</link><description>I review books, movies, games, and more.</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 03:57:34 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/reviews/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Tale of Despereaux</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/reviews/the-tale-of-despereaux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/reviews/the-tale-of-despereaux/</guid><description><![CDATA[


<aside class="admonition info">
    <div class="admonition__title">
        Info
    </div>
	<div class="admonition__content">
        <p>Full Name: The Tale of Desperaux being a story of a mouse, a princess, some soup, and a spool of thread.<br>
Author: Kate DiCamillo<br>
Illustrated by: Timothy Basil Ering</p>

    </div>
</aside>
<p>The Tale of Despereaux is an excellent book. The characters are adorable and very well developed. However, the ending seems to be very abrupt.</p>
<p>This story is set in a world where mice and rats can speak. It is wonderful to listen to what these animals have to say. Their behavior is portrayed very similar to human behavior. And just like humans, there are heroes and villains among mice and rats, who will go against the wind, do something incredible; because they want to do it, and are not influenced by what others say.</p>
<p>The writer frequently talks to the reader, often at the end of each chapter, making it more enticing to read ahead.</p>
<p>The book consists of four parts, the author calls it 4 books. In the first three books, the author introduces three main characters. Their history is well narrated, in quite detail. The story jumps forward and backward in time very often. This is not difficult to follow and adds to the narrative. The time jumps make it more interesting.  In the fourth book the three characters meet and have nice interactions. I felt that the ending was very short, not very detailed. It is sad because the reader wants to read more about these lovable characters. But then again, I understand that writing an ending is always the toughest part.</p>
<p>The book does have a lot of humorous moments, exaggeration that is totally unlikely and also slightly dark humor.</p>
<p>Overall, it was a very nice experience. I would rate it 7/10</p>



<aside class="admonition more-info">
    <div class="admonition__title">
        More info
    </div>
	<div class="admonition__content">
        <p>ISBN: 9708744598698<br>
Number of Pages: 270<br>
Publisher: Walker Books and subsidiaries<br>
Published: 2004<br>
Language: English<br>
Illustrations: Yes<br>
Ages: 9-12</p>

    </div>
</aside>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>