<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/research/</link><description/><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 19:21:58 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/research/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/tags/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2023 W18: Chai and Why?</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W18/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2023 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W18/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!</p>
<p>I had been busy the last few months writing a research paper. However, now, May is here, the paper is submitted, the semester has ended, and I have some free time on my hands.</p>
<h2 id="some-news-for-you">Some news for you</h2>
<h3 id="chai-and-why">Chai and Why</h3>
<p>I, along with Varun, Eeshan, and Ashutosh from the School of Technology and Computer Science in TIFR are organizing a fun outreach session of Chai and Why.
Entry is open and free for all!
See you tomorrow morning at 11, at Prithvi Café, Juhu.
<a href="https://www.tifr.res.in/~outreach/chai_and_why.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Read more about the Chai and Why series →</a>

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W18/cw_20230507.webp" alt="An informational poster about the Chai and Why session on May 7, 2023">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            Poster for the event
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

</p>
<h3 id="new-preprint">New preprint</h3>
<p>I have been working on a problem on stochastic games with window mean-payoff objectives with <a href="http://www.lsv.fr/~doyenhiba" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Laurent Doyen</a> and <a href="https://www.tifr.res.in/~shibashis.guha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Shibashis Guha</a> for the better part of the past year.
We finally finished writing the paper and uploaded a preprint on arXiv.org:
<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.11563" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Stochastic Window Mean-payoff Games</a>.
With this, I now have a page on <a href="https://dblp.org/pid/345/7987.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dblp</a>!

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W18/arxiv_swmp.webp" alt="A screenshot of the arXiv page of the preprint">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            A screenshot of the arXiv page.
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

</p>
<h3 id="final-space-ends">Final Space Ends</h3>
<p>When <em>Final Space</em> was unceremoniously cancelled after Season 3 with the biggest cliffhanger ever, it was a very sad day.
The good news now is that the creator of the show, Olan Rogers, is getting a chance to complete the story in the form of a graphic novel.
I highly recommend that you watch this show.
If you are outside the US, you can watch it on Netflix till December 2023.
You can <a href="https://finalspaceends.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pre-order the graphic novel</a> to support Olan for what will undoubtedly be an arduous road ahead.
Almost 20,000 copies have already been sold in less than two weeks.</p>
<h3 id="whats-playing">What&rsquo;s playing</h3>
<ul>
<li>The Broadway Musical <em>The Sound of Music</em> started playing in Mumbai from May 3. I watched it on the opening night and loved it. The acting, singing, and dancing by the cast is phenomenal. The live music by the orchestra was amazing as well.

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W18/sound_of_music_featured.webp" alt="The cast of The Sound of Music bowing on stage">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            The cast of the musical
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

</li>
<li>For some reason, all eight Harry Potter movies are back in theaters in Mumbai. I missed watching the first four movies in the theaters, so this is a chance to experience them on the big screen.</li>
<li>Guardians of the Galaxy Vol. 3 released this week as well. While I am no longer interested in the MCU, the reviews for this film are looking positive, and I might go watch it after all.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="some-interesting-videos">Some interesting videos</h2>
<p>Here are some videos were uploaded on YouTube in the last week that I liked.</p>
<h3 id="quirky-keyboards">Quirky keyboards</h3>
<ul>
<li>A video about the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BytowtVycc0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">history of the arrow keys on keyboards</a> by the 8-bit guy.
Almost every keyboard you can find today has arrow keys (or cursor keys) in an &ldquo;inverted T&rdquo; shape. However, this has not always been the case.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>There&rsquo;s something wrong with Joel Haver&rsquo;s friend&rsquo;s keyboard. It&rsquo;s not a typical QWERTY keyboard. He uses the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yWoDSsCX1S8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Blomfu keyboard</a>!</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="marbula-one-s4">Marbula One S4</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AtXf1yhf01k" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Season 4 of Marble racing begins!</a> It is fun to watch the marbles make laps across the track while listening to the captivating commentary.</p>
<h3 id="ai-generated-memes">AI generated memes</h3>
<p>YouTuber demonflyingfox became famous last month for creating AI generated videos on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iE39q-IKOzA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Harry Potter Balenciaga</a>.
Now they are back with another AI generated video on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ygWsjr9qhVc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Breaking Bad in German</a>. Wandlung zum Bösen!</p>
<h3 id="epic-npc-man">Epic NPC man</h3>
<p>Here&rsquo;s another epic NPC man video by VLDL. A bug in the programs of two NPC muggers in the town of Honeywood leads to a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IfzGbAh3nNI" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hilarious outcome</a>.</p>
<h3 id="elliot-is-a-cool-guy">Elliot is a cool guy</h3>
<p>Elliot, a graphic designer, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sAk9SZ9yrMY" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tries out a bunch of graphic design softwares</a> to make posters.
The programs that he tries out include Photoshop, Canva, Inkscape, GIMP, and even Excel.
My favourite one is of course Inkscape!</p>
<h3 id="book-graphs">Book graphs</h3>
<p>In this episode of Numberphile, James Grimes talks about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qw2Pl_Nk3CA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">book embeddings of graphs</a>.
These are an interesting generalization of planar graphs.
The vertices of a graph are placed in a single line that forms the &lsquo;spine&rsquo; of a book.
No two edges between two vertices allowed to intersect.
We can avoid edge intersections by embedding the edges in different &lsquo;pages&rsquo;.
The problem is, given a graph, to find the minimum number of pages required to embed the graph.
After watching the video, you can also read the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.07630" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the paper on arXiv</a>.
They show that four pages are sufficient to embed any planar graphs.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now! See you in the next one. &#x1f44b;</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Does it seem strange to see arrow keys in a line? The text editor vim does that. In vim, you can press <kbd>h</kbd>, <kbd>j</kbd>, <kbd>k</kbd>, <kbd>l</kbd> to move the cursor left, down, up, and right respectively.
I will be posting more tips about vim in the future.
Once you try vim, you cannot go back.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>