<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>sandwiches by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/sandwiches/</link><description/><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 01:03:27 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/sandwiches/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/tags/sandwiches/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Starfruit Sandwich</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/recipes/starfruit-sandwich/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/recipes/starfruit-sandwich/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<img src="https://pranshugaba.com/recipes/starfruit-sandwich/starfuit_sandwich_featured_hucab1bbb11ed33e4f58dd56fb89825fbc_1104066_1080x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" alt="" /><p>One day, many moons ago, I went out in Bangalore for a long walk and bought an assortment of groceries from different parts of the city: Organic spinach bread, starfruits, tomatoes, cheese cubes, rock salt, and a knife.</p>
<p>When I returned to my room, I tried to make a sandwich from what I had bought. The result: A delicious juicy sandwich with a variety of tastes and textures that is also easy to make.</p>
<p>The following recipe makes one sandwich. Two or three such sandwiches would make a meal.</p>
<h2 id="ingredients">Ingredients</h2>
<ul>
<li>2 slices of sliced bread (preferably spinach bread)</li>
<li>1 starfruit</li>
<li>1 tomato</li>
<li>1 cheese cube of 20g</li>
<li>Rock salt</li>
<li>Pringles (optional)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="directions">Directions</h2>
<ol>
<li>Cut a tomato into two halves. Cut one half into four slices. Keep the other half aside.</li>
<li>Arrange the tomato slices on a slice of bread.</li>
<li>Sprinkle some rock salt on the tomato slices.</li>
<li>Cut a starfruit into thin slices.</li>
<li>Place five starfruit slices in the shape of a star on the tomatoes. Keep the remaining slices aside.

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/recipes/starfruit-sandwich/starfruit_sandwich_open.jpg" alt="Tomato and starfruit slices placed on a slice of bread.">
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>
</li>
<li>Sprinkle some rock salt on the starfuit slices.</li>
<li>Cut a quarter of the cheese cube and keep it aside. Slice the remaining cube and place the slices over the starfruit.</li>
<li>Cover with a slice of bread, and cut diagonally into two triangles.

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/recipes/starfruit-sandwich/starfruit_sandwich_cut.jpg" >
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>
</li>
<li>Enjoy your starfruit sandwich! Intersperse with bites of tomato, starfruit, and cheese that you had kept aside.
Optionally, consume some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pringles" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hyperbolic paraboloid potato-based crisps</a> on the side.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="tips">Tips</h2>
<ul>
<li>Starfruit seeds are soft and are easily cut with a knife. Inspect the starfruit slices closely and make sure that you remove all seed fragments from the slices. A starfruit typically has 4-6 seeds in it.</li>
<li>If you don&rsquo;t have spinach bread, you may use whole wheat bread or multigrain bread instead. You can apply some mint chutney to the bread slices to make it tastier.</li>
<li>If you don&rsquo;t have starfruit available, you may use a cucumber instead. However, this is not as much fun.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><a href="/contact">Let me know</a> if you tried this recipe! Send pictures of how it turned out! Did you like it? Did you make some changes to the recipe? Feel free to share your own recipes with me as well!</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>