<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Links by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/links/</link><description/><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 05:05:22 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/links/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/tags/links/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SoME #2</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/some-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/some-2/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<h2 id="last-year">Last year</h2>
<p>Last summer, <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Grant Sanderson of 3Blue1Brown</a> held a contest named SoME #1. The name is short for <em>The Summer of Math Exposition</em>. In this contest, Grant asked people to submit maths explainers &mdash; something that explains a concept in maths (or physics or computer science). This explainer could be of any form: a short video, a blog post, an interactive webpage, or even a game! The goal of this contest was to encourage more people to create explainers.</p>
<p>There are multiple benefits to this. One, it improves the collection of resources available to all for learning new things (More than a 1000 entries were submitted!). Everyone has a different learning style, and similarly, everyone has a different teaching style. Even if someone has made a video explaining a particular concept, the way you explain the same topic will be different. Some people will find their content easier to understand, and some will find your content easier to understand. The more high-quality content there is out there, the higher the chance that you will find something that you can connect to.</p>
<p>Secondly, when you explain a concept to someone else, you tend to dispel misconceptions you may have had about the topic, and you might find an easier way of thinking about a problem as you try to present it in a simple manner for the explainer. You are bound to learn something new and improve your own understanding of the subject. It is a win-win-win for everybody!</p>
<p>You can <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/blog/some1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">read more about last year&rsquo;s contest on Grant&rsquo;s website</a>.
You can also find <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/blog/some1-results#all-entries" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a list of all submitted entries</a> there. You can read/watch them at your leisure and learn many things new.</p>
<h2 id="this-year">This year</h2>
<p>The #1 in SoME #1 suggested that this could be a recurring event, and sure enough, it&rsquo;s back this year as SoME #2.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hZuYICAEN9Y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch the announcement video by Grant on YouTube →</a></p>
<p>Not much has changed from last year.
This time, there is an additional platform to help domain experts to collaborate with content producers.
A repository has been setup on GitHub to help people with complementary skills to find and connect with each other.</p>
<p>For example, say you are well-versed in topology and would like to make a game related to something in topology, but don&rsquo;t know how to make games. You can request for a game developer on the GitHub page. Similarly, if you are good at making videos but don&rsquo;t know what to make the video about, you can look for a domain expert who would like to get a video made. By collaborating with others, you can make something amazing, something that would be impossible working on your own.</p>
<p>Here are some important links for this year&rsquo;s SoME:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://summerofmathexposition.substack.com/p/the-summer-of-math-exposition-is" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contest rules and details</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/leios/SoME_Topics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub for collaboration and matchmaking</a></li>
<li><a href="https://discord.gg/dsp3zgB4qQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Discord for general discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfeYb0k8wr14WkMWYaeYpw6iiygOqA-Jwi_YMNPgRVJzMPOoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submission form</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The deadline for submitting your work is 15th August 2022.
Five winners will be selected who each will be awarded a Golden Pi creature and a prize money of $1000 sponsored by Brilliant. Very exciting!</p>
<p>I will not have time to make a video this year, but I will write a series on the <em>Determinacy of Two-player Games with Perfect Information</em>. The topic is inspired by some papers that I recently read that were written by Gale and Stewart and by Donald Martin. I will upload the series on this site.</p>
<p>Good luck! I hope you make some awesome maths explainers!</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Research Seminars</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/research-seminars/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 02:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/research-seminars/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Most research talks are being held online post lockdown, and as a result, one can access talks from all over the world.
I came across a website that lists upcoming research seminars and makes it easier to discover interesting talks.</p>
<p><a href="https://researchseminars.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://researchseminars.org/</a></p>
<p>This website was launched in April 2020 shortly after lockdown began.
It lists upcoming talks and seminars held in universities all over the world.
You can filter talks by topic, language, institution, and more.</p>

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/articles/research-seminars/research-seminars.png" alt="Screenshot of the homepage of researchseminars.org">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            Screenshot of the homepage of researchseminars.org
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>For each talk, the site shows details such as the title, abstract, speaker, the targeted audience, and a link to the seminar&rsquo;s website.
Most talks have a livestream link available (either interactive like Zoom / Google Meet / Microsoft Teams or viewing only such as Youtube).
Links for some talks are not be available unless you register on this site.</p>
<p>Try to attend and participate in talks that pique your interest. The feeling of being able to attend a talk held halfway across the world is unmatched.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Advent Puzzles 2021</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/advent-puzzles-2021/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 05:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/advent-puzzles-2021/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>December is here, which means it&rsquo;s problem solving season!</p>
<h2 id="maths">Maths</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.mscroggs.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew Scroggs</a> has posted the seventh edition of the <a href="https://www.mscroggs.co.uk/blog/91" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Advent calendar of maths puzzles</a> on his blog. A new puzzle is unlocked everyday, and you have until the end of the year to submit the answers. The first twenty-four puzzles each have a three digit solutions, and these solutions form the clues required to solve the main puzzle on the 25th.
Ten people who solve all puzzles correctly are randomly selected to win a T-shirt!</p>
<p>The problems are mostly from number theory and combinatorics, which are coincidentally two of my favourite areas of mathematics. I believe most people would find the problems interesting and challenging. I have solved the last three editions of this advent, and plan to solve it this year as well.</p>
<h2 id="programming">Programming</h2>
<p>This year, we get the seventh <a href="https://adventofcode.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Advent of Code</a> by <a href="http://was.tl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Eric Wastl</a>. Two programming puzzles are unlocked every day.
Solving these puzzles requires basic programming skills, but more importantly, critical thinking skills.
You are free to use any programming language to solve them. You can even use pen and paper, although I would not recommend it.
I recently started learning the functional programming language Haskell, and I am using it to solve these puzzles. I am loving the experience so far.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you know any other puzzles happening in December (or any other time of the year really), <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/contact/">let me know</a>!</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>