<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Games by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/games/</link><description/><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 16:31:26 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/tags/games/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/tags/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2023 W42: Shadow of the Moon</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W42/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W42/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!</p>
<p>I hope you have been doing well in the past few months.
This was the 42nd week of the year, which means that the end of the year is nigh.
Indeed, as the wise Ford Prefect once said, &ldquo;Time is an illusion. Lunchtime, doubly so.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Please enjoy this new issue of my newsletter!
There is a lot that is new on my site. I have also included several interesting links, some of which you might enjoy.</p>
<aside class="[ toc ] [ plain-link border-medium border-radius-large ]">
  <details open>
    <summary>
      <h2 class="toc__heading">Table of Contents</h2>
    </summary>
    <nav id="TableOfContents">
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#whats-new-with-me">What&rsquo;s new with me</a>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#new-tablet">New tablet</a></li>
        <li><a href="#apprendre-le-français">Apprendre le français</a></li>
        <li><a href="#new-photopoems">New photopoems</a></li>
        <li><a href="#new-comic">New comic</a></li>
        <li><a href="#books--tv-shows">Books / TV shows</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li><a href="#curated-content-for-you">Curated content for you</a>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#pictures-of-the-solar-eclipse">Pictures of the solar eclipse</a></li>
        <li><a href="#youtube-videos">YouTube videos</a></li>
        <li><a href="#a-game">A game</a></li>
        <li><a href="#a-song">A song</a></li>
        <li><a href="#and-an-excerpt">And an excerpt</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
</nav>
  </details>
</aside>

<h2 id="whats-new-with-me">What&rsquo;s new with me</h2>
<h3 id="new-tablet">New tablet</h3>
<p>I used to use an iPad with an Apple Pencil to jot down notes.
However, the Pencil broke, and a new one is not cheap.
I decided to get a new tablet, an Android this time.
I am loving it so far.
I will write a post sharing my experience with the new tab soon.</p>
<h3 id="apprendre-le-français">Apprendre le français</h3>
<p>One of <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W01/#languages">my goals this year</a> has been to learn more languages.
One of the languages I want to get better at is français, that is, French.
I had learnt some French in school, but I was not very good at it, and I had forgotten most of it by now anyway.
I resumed actively learning French a few months ago.</p>
<p>To improve my writing skills, I will post short essays in French here on my site in a section called <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/a-propos-de-moi/"><em>À propos de moi</em></a>, which means <em>About me</em> in French.
I have written <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/a-propos-de-moi/on-commence/">the first essay</a> already where I briefly introduce myself in French.
I will write about interesting events in my life, as well as document my French learning experience, all of it in French.
If you are a French speaker, please have a read and let me know if you find mistakes or have suggestions to improve my writing.</p>
<h3 id="new-photopoems">New photopoems</h3>
<p>This week, I posted two new photopoems: <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/barcode/">a haiku</a> and <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/the-nine-bollards-with-faces/">a limerick</a>.
Here is one of the photos.</p>

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W42/bollards.webp" alt="Nine bollards, each with eyes and a mouth spray painted on.">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            Nine bollards, each with eyes and a mouth spray painted on.
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<h3 id="new-comic">New comic</h3>
<p>I had drawn <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/comics/1/">a comic</a> about ghosts a long long time ago, during lockdown.
The new tablet has inspired me to pick up drawing once again.
I have drawn a <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/comics/2/">new comic</a> with the same characters.</p>

<figure class="large">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W42/comic-2.webp" alt="No one likes being ghosted. Not even ghosts.">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            No one likes being ghosted. Not even ghosts.
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<h3 id="books--tv-shows">Books / TV shows</h3>
<ul>
<li>I have started reading a novel titled <em>Riddley Walker</em> by Russell Hoban.
It may not look like it is written in English, but it (mostly) makes sense if you read it out aloud.
It takes quite a bit of effort to read and understand it though.</li>
<li>I have been watching more of British TV panel shows lately.
I am currently on Richard Osman&rsquo;s House of Games (Series 7), Taskmaster (Series 16), Only Connect, and University Challenge (Series 53).
These are all immensely entertaining.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="curated-content-for-you">Curated content for you</h2>
<h3 id="pictures-of-the-solar-eclipse">Pictures of the solar eclipse</h3>
<p>There was an annular solar eclipse last week that was visible from some parts of the Americas.
Thanks to NASA, we get to see images of the eclipse from two unusual perspectives.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-detail/gmt288_01_16_jasmin-moghbeli_sn1063_annular-eclipse-second-pass-2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The solar eclipse from the International Space Station</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nasa.gov/image-detail/eclipse-annular-epc-2023287-lrg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A picture of the Earth with the shadow of the Moon</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="youtube-videos">YouTube videos</h3>
<h4 id="geoguessr-world-cup">GeoGuessr world cup</h4>
<p><a href="https://www.geoguessr.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GeoGuessr</a> is a game where you are shown a Google Street View image.
You must look around for clues (such as landmarks, road signs, the flora and the fauna) to sleuth out your location on the globe.
It is a lot of fun.
I love playing this game and watching others play it too.
One of my favourite players to watch is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TVt1GKBZMzc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GeoWizard</a>.</p>
<p>The first ever <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0OzZOrs8wmcPWwL2JD3kXRLRVFcbD1uU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GeoGuessr world cup</a> happened this week.
It was a massive event, with players from all around the world.
The matches had live commentary and there was a huge prize pool of over $50,000.
It was thrilling to see the pros battle it out.</p>
<h4 id="an-epic-game-of-rock-paper-scissors">An epic game of Rock Paper Scissors</h4>
<p>CGP Grey has posted a challenge where you must <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PmWQmZXYd74" target="_blank" rel="noopener">play a series of games of Rock, Paper, Scissors</a> with him.
You win if you can win 20 games in a row.
Can you devise a strategy to beat him?
Will Lady Luck be on your side?
See how far you can get.
Don&rsquo;t cheat.</p>
<p>Assuming that you win each game with chance 1/3, the probability that you win twenty games in a row is roughly 1 in 3.5 billion.
It is <em>highly</em> unlikely that anyone will able to achieve this feat.
Also keep in mind that he uses mind tricks to affect your decision.
Regardless of how many games you win, it is a fun game to play.
With millions of people expected to play this game, we are in for some juicy statistics.</p>
<h4 id="a-poetic-review">A poetic review</h4>
<p><em>Cocoon</em> is a new indie puzzle game directed by a designer of the games <em>Limbo</em> and <em>Inside</em>.
The gameplay looks stunning, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=efgBO69P1Kw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">videogamedunkey&rsquo;s review</a> is just poetry.</p>
<h4 id="bat-canned">Bat-canned</h4>
<p>What happens when Bale Batman fires Pattinson Batman?
Watch the two amazing comedians Pete Holmes and Thomas Middleditch in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zs66p5jQ9dM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Batman fires The Batman</a>.
Also check out another series by Pete Holmes called <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLBIeL6Ot52KOPa87HrwLgtSF3lLczz_9E" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Ex-Men</em></a> where he parodies characters from the X-Men series, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MDdHYjb5sBk" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Badman</em></a> where he parodies Batman.</p>
<h4 id="the-holy-grail">The Holy Grail</h4>
<p>It is the 48th and ½ anniversary of Monty Python and the Holy Grail, so the movie is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4b52A3sKz-I" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rereleasing in theaters</a> once again.
Unfortunately, it seems like it will only release in theaters in the United States and for two days only.</p>
<h3 id="a-game">A game</h3>
<p>The New York Times now has <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/games/connections" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a new game called &ldquo;Connections&rdquo;</a>.
If you are a viewer of the quiz show Only Connect, you may already be familiar with this game.
You are given a wall of sixteen seemingly unrelated words/phrases, and your goal is to divide the clues into four groups of four clues each, each with some connection.
This games can get tricky because of red herring, which are clues that may belong to more than one connection.
Sometimes, it is difficult to see any connections between the clues at all, while at other times you may find five, or even six, clues satisfying the same connection.</p>
<p>It is fun to play this everyday.
I wish they would credit Only Connect for the format of the game.
You can only play the current day&rsquo;s game on The New York Times&rsquo; website.
There is another website where you can <a href="https://connections.swellgarfo.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">play past puzzles</a>.
On this site, you can also create your own puzzles and share them with others.</p>
<h3 id="a-song">A song</h3>
<p><em>Beautiful Mind</em>, a new song by Tom Cardy &amp; the magnificent Brian David Gilbert<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3w1wwGcu0Dk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></p>
<h3 id="and-an-excerpt">And an excerpt</h3>
<p>Do you know how far New Zealand is from Australia?
The answer may surprise you.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If it would not look too much like showing off, I would tell the reader where New Zealand is; for he is as I was; he thinks he knows. And he thinks he knows where Hertzegovina is; and how to pronounce pariah; and how to use the word unique without exposing himself to the derision of the dictionary. But in truth, he knows none of these things
<cite>&ndash; Excerpt from Chapter XXVI, Following the Equator by Mark Twain</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Do you think New Zealand is close to Australia or Asia? Read on&hellip;</p>
<blockquote>
<p>All people think that New Zealand is close to Australia or Asia, or somewhere, and that you cross to it on a bridge. But that is not so. It is not close to anything, but lies by itself, out in the water. It is nearest to Australia, but still not near. The gap between is very wide. It will be a surprise to the reader, as it was to me, to learn that the distance from Australia to New Zealand is really twelve or thirteen hundred miles, and that there is no bridge.
<cite>&ndash; Another excerpt from Chapter XXVI, Following the Equator</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I would recommend that you read the entire chapter, and if possible, the entire book.
It&rsquo;s absolutely hilarious, and you also get to learn a ton of obscure 19th century geography facts.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now! See you in the next one. &#x1f44b;</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>2023 W01: Adieu 2022 / Welcome 2023</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W01/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W01/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>The year 2022 is over, and a new year has begun.
In this issue of my newsletter, I share some highlights of the past year, as well as some goals that I have set for the coming year.</p>
<p>As always, if you would like to read previous issues, you can do so at <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/">https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter</a></p>
<h2 id="my-highlights-of-2022">My highlights of 2022</h2>
<h3 id="travel-in-2022">Travel in 2022</h3>
<p>I travelled to a fair share of new places in 2022.</p>
<h4 id="kolkata">Kolkata</h4>
<p>I went to a friends&rsquo; wedding in Kolkata in April. It was my first visit to the city, and I loved the sights and the foods there.
I walked across the Hooghly river along the Howrah bridge, bought novels from College street, and ate some roadside phuchka.

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W01/kolkata_bridge.webp" alt="Walking across the Hooghly along the Howrah bridge">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            Walking across the Hooghly along the Howrah bridge
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

</p>
<h4 id="israel">Israel</h4>
<p>I attended the <a href="https://www.floc2022.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FLoC conference</a> in Haifa, Israel in August.
This was my first time in a new country on my own and it was an amazing experience.</p>
<p>Haifa is one of the most beautiful cities I have ever been to.
The city sits on a hill, which means that walking in the city is akin to trekking.
Haifa also abuts the beautiful Mediterranean sea and it was a delight to swim in those cool blue waters.
While I missed some of the Indian spices in the food there, I loved the bread, the hummus, and the falafels.

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W01/haifa_pano_featured.webp" alt="A panorama of the city of Haifa and the port">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            A panorama of the city of Haifa and the port
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

</p>
<h4 id="chennai">Chennai</h4>
<p>I attended the <a href="https://www.fsttcs.org.in/2022/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FSTTCS conference</a> in IIT Madras in December.
The campus of IIT Madras (along with Guindy national park) is a literally a forest in the middle of the city and is teeming with deer and monkeys.
I had never seen so many deer up close before.</p>
<p>Chennai is great city to go for a walk in.
I went for a <a href="https://madrasinherited.in/walk/kutchery/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">heritage walk</a> on Kutchery road in Mylapore where I learnt about the rich history of the various shops and establishments in that locality.

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2023-W01/chennai_pano.webp" alt="A panorama of Marina beach from atop the Chennai lighthouse">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            A panorama of Marina beach from atop the Chennai lighthouse
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

</p>
<h3 id="books-in-2022">Books in 2022</h3>
<p>After a slump of 4 years, I picked up reading this year again.
Here are some of the books that I read this year and particularly enjoyed:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>The Stranger</em> by Albert Camus<br>
A short novella in two parts. A very interesting read. I cannot say anything more about this book without spoiling it.</li>
<li><em>A Terrible Book</em> by Jay Micheal<br>
This bellyachingly hilarious book is a parody of almost every literary trope that exists. It is available as an eBook for $0.99 on Kindle, and nowhere else. The author remains elusive, but it is not for a lack of trying. I am not able to find any information about the author other than his short bio and brilliantly drawn self-portrait on this book&rsquo;s listing on Amazon.</li>
<li><em>Crime and Punishment</em> by Fyodor Dostoevsky<br>
This book shares themes with <em>The Stranger</em>.
This book is about what drives a man to kill a person, and the mental anguish that he suffers as a consequence.
The plot slows down and is drawn out at times, but I think that it is necessary to better understand the plight of the antihero.</li>
<li><em>The Book Thief</em> by Markus Zusak<br>
Set during the Second World War, this story follows the life of a little girl living in Nazi Germany who loves to read books. A tale narrated by Death himself, you can&rsquo;t not read this.</li>
<li><em>Project Hail Mary</em> by Andy Weir<br>
While this book is science fiction, but it doesn&rsquo;t read as such.
Everything that happens in the story seems scientifically plausible; you might as well be reading the logs of a real astronaut.
It is great to see the thought process of the protagonist as he tackles the problems he encounters.
Once I started reading it, it was downright impossible to put it down.
I finished reading it in less than three days.</li>
<li><em>Elantris</em> by Brandon Sanderson<br>
This is a fantasy novel and one of the first books published by Brandon Sanderson.
The story is told through the points-of-view of three characters: a prince, a princess, and a priest, each having different motives and personalities.
It is particularly fun when these characters interact and you experience the same scene from different viewpoints.
I also loved the magic system in this story.
This is a standalone book and a complete story on its own. All in all, it&rsquo;s a very satisfying and thrilling book.</li>
<li><em>The Sword of Kaigen</em> by M. L. Wang<br>
This is a fantasy book with a Japanesque setting.
I could feel some vibes of  <em>Avatar: The Last Airbender</em> while reading this book, primarily because some characters can manipulate the elements around them.
If you liked that show, then you will probably enjoy reading this book.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are many more books that I have read and would like to read.
You can have a look at my <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/reads/">reading list</a> that I regularly keep up-to-date.</p>
<h3 id="tv-shows-and-movies-in-2022">TV Shows and Movies in 2022</h3>
<p>It was a great year for movies and TV Shows.
Here are some of my favourites of the year.</p>
<h4 id="tv-shows">TV Shows</h4>
<ul>
<li><em>Barry (season 3)</em><br>
The penultimate season of the series.
This show is an unusual combination of drama and comedy, where the eponymous character Barry is both an actor and an assassin.
Now, his worlds are about to collide.
Barry is played by Bill Hader who is amazing in this role.
He also writes and directs some of the episodes.</li>
<li><em>The Rehearsal (season 1)</em><br>
A masterpiece by Nathan Fielder. Very meta. It is safe to say that this show is like none other. I was surprised to find out that there will be another season of this show.</li>
<li><em>Better Call Saul (season 6)</em><br>
A satisfying end to the chicanery of Saul Goodman and to the Breaking Bad universe. It&rsquo;s all gone now. Bravo Vince!</li>
<li><em>House of the Dragon (season 1)</em><br>
I will be honest, my expectations for this show were super low after seeing how <em>Game of Thrones</em> ended.
However, I was convinced otherwise before the first episode ended.
This show has a lot of plotting, stabbing, and backstabbing, and keeps you at the edge of your seat.
George R. R. Martin is, of course, a masterful story teller, and the showrunners Ryan Condal and Miguel Sapochnik have done an excellent job translating it to screen.
A special shout-out to Paddy Considine, who was phenomenal as King Viserys.
This was a rare occurence where I watched the show before reading the book.
I have got to read <em>Fire and Blood</em> now.</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="movies">Movies</h4>
<ul>
<li><em>The Unbearable Weight of Massive Talent</em><br>
An amazing action-comedy movie starring Nicholas Cage as Nick Cage, as well as Pedro Pascal. This is a fun movie to watch.</li>
<li><em>Chello Show</em><br>
A Gujarati movie about a boy fascinated by movies.</li>
<li><em>Bullet Train</em><br>
Another action-comedy movie. As the name suggests, this almost entirely takes place on a bullet train. This movie has great action sequences, and the dialogue and story are quite good too.</li>
<li><em>Glass Onion</em><br>
While I didn&rsquo;t like it as much as <em>Knives Out</em>, it was still entertaining to see Detective Benoit Blanc back on screen.</li>
<li><em>The Menu</em><br>
Anya Tayloy-Joy and Ralph Fiennes are great in this, and so are the supporting cast.
Not sure if this is a horror or a comedy.
It is definitely absurd.
A culinary delight.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="games-in-2022">Games in 2022</h3>
<p>Some games that I discovered and enjoyed playing this year:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Duotrigordle / Redactle / Worldle</em><br>
Wordle became popular at the start of this year, and we saw many new *le games.
These were the ones that I played the most.</li>
<li><em>NYTimes spelling bee and crossword</em><br>
I try to solve the NYT Spelling Bee daily and the crossword whenever I can. I can usually only solve the Mondays and Tuesdays crosswords.</li>
<li><em>Dark Souls</em><br>
I started playing Dark Souls. I was initially hesitant, or even scared to play it. However, the Souls-like games are so good and they have spoiled most other games for me. Praise the sun! \o/</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="my-goals-for-2023">My goals for 2023</h2>
<p>I have set some goals for myself for this year.</p>
<h3 id="reading-and-writing">Reading and writing</h3>
<p>I would like to write more often and on a regular basis.
I want to be uploading new content on this website more frequently.
I also want to read more books this year.</p>
<h3 id="getting-fit">Getting fit</h3>
<p>I will start going to the gym or cycling regularly.</p>
<h3 id="languages">Languages</h3>
<p>I want to learn more languages and become a hyperpolyglot.
I plan to achieve</p>
<ul>
<li>native fluency in ગુજરાતી,</li>
<li>moderate fluency in français, and</li>
<li>basic conversational fluency in मराठी and Deutsch.</li>
</ul>
<p>I will use flashcards and Rosetta Stone to improve my vocabulary and grammar.
I will also try to read literature, watch movies, and connect with native speakers to practice and get better at these languages.</p>
<h3 id="game-development">Game development</h3>
<p>I want to get good at game development.
By the end of the year, I want to be comfortable enough with the game engine Godot that creating simple arcade style games such as Tetris, Pacman, and Flappy Bird are second-nature to me.
I would also like to make and publish one or two moderately complex games.
I would need to collaborate with someone for the aspects of gamedev that are not my fortes such as pixel art and sound design.</p>
<hr>
<p>I will also post some short term goals, and from time to time share updates on how I am progressing along these goals for 2023.
<a href="https://pranshugaba.com/contact/">Let me know</a> what have you planned for this new year!</p>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now! See you in the next one. &#x1f44b;</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>2022 W28: New Space Images</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!</p>
<p>I am back after a bit of a break. To make up for it, here&rsquo;s a longer than usual issue of my newsletter where I share updates about me, this site, and other miscellaneous things.
Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s new since the last issue:</p>
<h2 id="recent-updates">Recent updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Grant Sanderson of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3Blue1Brown" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3Blue1Brown</a> is back this year with another Summer of Maths Exposition (SoME #2). The goal of this contest is to encourage people to create some awesome maths explainers. You can <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/articles/some-2/">read my article on SoME #2</a> for more details about the contest. There&rsquo;s only one month left to submit your explainers, so this is a good time to get started!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The GMTK Game Jam 2022 is live! The GMTK game jam started in 2017 and has been taking place every year in July since then. The theme of this year&rsquo;s jam is &ldquo;Roll of the Dice&rdquo;. You must create and share a playable game based on the theme in less than 50 hours. It is not easy to create a game that works and is also fun to play in this short period of time, and yet each year, we see some amazing games come out of these game jams.<br>
<a href="https://itch.io/jam/gmtk-jam-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Read more about the GMTK game jam 2022 →</a></p>
<p>Only 24 of the 50 hours of the jam are left at the time of writing this post, so it would be difficult for you to submit a game for this game jam if you didn&rsquo;t know about it before. You can, however, play the games submitted in the jam and vote for the ones you like. You can also start preparing for next year&rsquo;s GMTK game jam. GMTK&rsquo;s YouTube channel is great place to learn about concepts in game design. Pick a game engine such as Godot or Bevy and start making your own game!</p>
<p>The GMTK game jam is only one of the very many game jams that happen. You can find more <a href="https://itch.io/jams" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jams on itch.io</a>. The schedule is jam-packed with game jams. There is always some jam in progress and some upcoming jams that you can look forward to participate in.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Speaking of games, I started playing <em>Sekiro: Shadows Die Twice</em>.
It&rsquo;s another masterpiece by From Software. In this game, you are a Shinobi warrior in Japan trying to fight Dragonrot.</p>
<p>It is a fun and exciting game that rewards persistence, determination, and exploration. The game seems terrifyingly difficult, and at times, even impossible. However, you must remember that the developers of this game are on your side. They want you to succeed. Keep trying! You will learn something with each death, you <em>will</em> get better at this game. When you finally defeat that difficult boss that you were stuck on for so long, it&rsquo;s the best feeling in the world.</p>

  <figure >
      
      
      
      
      
      <picture>
          
          <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/sekiro_1.jpg" alt="Wolf is standing ready to fight the boss Lady Butterfly.">
      </picture>
      
      
      <figcaption>
          
              I am down to my last of health and I have used up all health potions and pellets after defeating a difficult boss. I realise to my horror that the boss has a second phase.
              
              
              
          
      </figcaption>
      
  </figure>
  

<p>Sekiro differs from the Dark Souls games in many aspects. Unlike Dark Souls, this game has only one weapon, the sword. It does not punish you for teleporting to the last checkpoint. The game let&rsquo;s you die once and resurrect without having to start from the last checkpoint. There is no stamina meter, you can keep sprinting without tiring. There is even a jump button in this game!</p>
<p>And yet, it is a From Software game at heart. The combat is fun, you will die again and again and again, dying will hurt as you will lose your precious skill points and coints, and of course, there is no difficulty setting. I have played it for about 15 hours and am stuck on some difficult bosses, but I am confident I will be able to defeat them all.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I watched <em>Minions: The Rise of Gru</em> last week. It was a delight to hear Steve Carell&rsquo;s voice as Young Gru. I also loved that we got to meet the younger versions of many characters from the Despicable Me movies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>This is a great time to be watching TV shows.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first episode of <em>Better Call Saul</em> after the mid-season break premiered last Monday. The episode was one hour long, but it was so packed with action that it only felt like five minutes. I was holding my breath and was on the edge of my seat the whole time. The story is approaching the start of Breaking Bad when we first see Saul in that show. There are only five episodes left and the show will be over in five weeks. I will be sad when this show ends :(</li>
<li>Volume 2 of <em>Stranger Things 4</em> came out on July 1. Unfortunately for me, some details of the ending were spoiled for me, but I enjoyed watching the show nonetheless.</li>
<li>Season 2 of <em>Only Murders in the Building</em> is going on. It is as intriguing as the first season. Steve Martin and Martin Short are an amazing duo.</li>
<li>The first two episodes of season 4 of <em>What We Do in the Shadows</em> premiered this Tuesday. Nadja, Nandor, Lazlo, and Gizmo are all reunited once again!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>I wrote a photopoem titled <em>rain train</em>. Here&rsquo;s the photo

  <figure class="medium">
      
      
      
      
      
      <picture>
          
          <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/rain-train.webp" alt="A train pulls into a station on a rainy day.">
      </picture>
      
      
  </figure>
  

and <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/rain-train/">here&rsquo;s the poem →</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="some-fun-stuff-for-you">Some fun stuff for you</h2>
<h3 id="jwst-images">JWST images</h3>
<p>The first photographs taken by James Webb Space Telescope were released this week. They look beautiful. This one&rsquo;s my favourite:

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/webb.webp" alt="Carina nebula">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            The Carina Nebula
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


Check out the <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/webbfirstimages/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">full resolutions images on NASA&rsquo;s website →</a></p>
<h3 id="youtube-videos">YouTube videos</h3>
<p>Here are some YouTube videos that I watched and enjoyed recently:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the latest episode of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8q_05PUYv1o&amp;list=PLNYkxOF6rcIAKIQFsNbV0JDws_G_bnNo9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">HTTP 203</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9qen5CKjUe8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cassie Evans talks to Jake about about SVG paths</a> and what the various letters and symbols in an SVG file mean. The SVG format is similar to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtle_graphics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Turtle graphics</a> most commonly seen in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logo_%28programming_language%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Logo programming language</a>. I am loving the new episodes of HTTP 203, but this does not mean I don&rsquo;t miss Surma.</li>
<li>I used to <em>love</em> playing the Harry Potter games on PC. Which is why I was delighted when I found this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f-A2XlJsC84" target="_blank" rel="noopener">interview with Christo Vuchetich, a game designer who worked on the Harry Potter PC games</a>. It is incredible how the game was made in a year with very little access to how the Harry Potter movies would look like. An interview on the Chamber of Secrets game is coming soon.  I cannot wait to watch it.</li>
<li>The team at Polygon play a game of Clay-O-Rama which is like DnD, but the players make clay figurines of their characters. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AbEBGf1J_qw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Simone, Pat, and Christina play the game with Jenna as their DM</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B0dDjz9lDYQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Steve Carell talks about some moments and scenes from the Despicable Me and Minions movies</a>.</li>
<li>Fractals are beautiful! But what are they? <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ofFLYfUEPVE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Keenan Crane, a computer scientist from CMU, explains what are fractals in 5 different levels of difficulty</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="online-games">Online games</h3>
<p>You may enjoy playing these games:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Regular tic-tac-toe becomes boring after a while. If both players play optimally, then the game will end in a tie. I would like to introduce you to a bidding version of the same game. In regular tic-tac-toe, both players take turns alternatingly to place their respective symbol on the grid. In the bidding version, both players start with a limited fund of say 100 points. At the start of each turn, they both bid some points. The player with the higher bid gets to place their symbol on the grid but must pay their bid amount to the other player.</p>
<p>The players must not only decide where to place their symbol in their turn in case they win the bid, but they must also decide how much to bid. Should they go all in in the start and occupy a good starting square? Or should they save their points for the endgame to play several turns at one and deliver a deathblow? You can try it yourself and play with a friend on this website: <a href="http://biddingttt.herokuapp.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bidding TTT</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You might have played the game Wordle where you try to guess a word in 5 tries. You may like <a href="https://www.quordle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quordle</a> more. In this game, you are required to guess four words within nine guesses. In case this was not enough, you can try <a href="https://duotrigordle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Duotrigordle</a>. In this game, you must guess 32 words and you have 37 guesses to do so.  It was surprised to find that Duotrigordle was easier than Quordle.  Let me know which variant of Wordle is your favourite.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="two-songs">Two songs</h3>
<p>Here are two songs from Eurovision that you may enjoy:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Moskau</em> by Dschinghis Khan, Eurovision 1979<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i0xOSxgs6w8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></li>
<li><em>Fairytale</em> by Alexander Rybek, Eurovision 2009<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WXwgZL4zx9o" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week! See you in the next one. &#x1f44b;</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Mini #4</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/minis/4/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 16:20:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/minis/4/</guid><description>
&lt;p>I foolishly tried to fight the guy near the bonfire in Lordran and he killed me almost immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I respawned, and he was still trying to kill me. I jumped off a cliff, and so did he. I respawned, but he did not :)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mini #3</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/minis/3/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 12:05:19 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/minis/3/</guid><description>
&lt;p>I started playing Dark Souls today. It is not as hard as I expected but, then again, I have only completed the tutorial.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the best tutorials I have seen in a game, despite being jump scared by a rolling boulder.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>