<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Newsletter by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/</link><description>New issues every Saturday</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 10:18:45 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>New Space Images</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!</p>
<p>I am back after a bit of a break. To make up for it, here&rsquo;s a longer than usual issue of my newsletter where I share updates about me, this site, and other miscellaneous things.
Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s new since the last issue:</p>
<h2 id="recent-updates">Recent updates</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Grant Sanderson of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/3Blue1Brown" target="_blank" rel="noopener">3Blue1Brown</a> is back this year with another Summer of Maths Exposition (SoME #2). The goal of this contest is to encourage people to create some awesome maths explainers. You can <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/posts/some-2/">read my post on SoME #2</a> for more details about the contest. There&rsquo;s only one month left to submit your explainers, so this is a good time to get started!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The GMTK Game Jam 2022 is live! The GMTK game jam started in 2017 and has been taking place every year in July since then. The theme of this year&rsquo;s jam is &ldquo;Roll of the Dice&rdquo;. You must create and share a playable game based on the theme in less than 50 hours. It is not easy to create a game that works and is also fun to play in this short period of time, and yet each year, we see some amazing games come out of these game jams.<br>
<a href="https://itch.io/jam/gmtk-jam-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Read more about the GMTK game jam 2022 →</a></p>
<p>Only 24 of the 50 hours of the jam are left at the time of writing this post, so it would be difficult for you to submit a game for this game jam if you didn&rsquo;t know about it before. You can, however, play the games submitted in the jam and vote for the ones you like. You can also start preparing for next year&rsquo;s GMTK game jam. GMTK&rsquo;s YouTube channel is great place to learn about concepts in game design. Pick a game engine such as Godot or Bevy and start making your own game!</p>
<p>The GMTK game jam is only one of the very many game jams that happen. You can find more <a href="https://itch.io/jams" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jams on itch.io</a>. The schedule is jam-packed with game jams. There is always some jam in progress and some upcoming jams that you can look forward to participate in.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Speaking of games, I started playing <em>Sekiro: Shadows Die Twice</em>.
It&rsquo;s another masterpiece by From Software. In this game, you are a Shinobi warrior in Japan trying to fight Dragonrot.</p>
<p>It is a fun and exciting game that rewards persistence, determination, and exploration. The game seems terrifyingly difficult, and at times, even impossible. However, you must remember that the developers of this game are on your side. They want you to succeed. Keep trying! You will learn something with each death, you <em>will</em> get better at this game. When you finally defeat that difficult boss that you were stuck on for so long, it&rsquo;s the best feeling in the world.</p>

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/sekiro_1.jpg" alt="Wolf is standing ready to fight the boss Lady Butterfly.">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
        
            I am down to my last of health and I have used up all health potions and pellets after defeating a difficult boss. I realise to my horror that the boss has a second phase.
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Sekiro differs from the Dark Souls games in many aspects. Unlike Dark Souls, this game has only one weapon, the sword. It does not punish you for teleporting to the last checkpoint. The game let&rsquo;s you die once and resurrect without having to start from the last checkpoint. There is no stamina meter, you can keep sprinting without tiring. There is even a jump button in this game!</p>
<p>And yet, it is a From Software game at heart. The combat is fun, you will die again and again and again, dying will hurt as you will lose your precious skill points and coints, and of course, there is no difficulty setting. I have played it for about 15 hours and am stuck on some difficult bosses, but I am confident I will be able to defeat them all.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I watched <em>Minions: The Rise of Gru</em> last week. It was a delight to hear Steve Carell&rsquo;s voice as Young Gru. I also loved that we got to meet the younger versions of many characters from the Despicable Me movies.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>This is a great time to be watching TV shows.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first episode of <em>Better Call Saul</em> after the mid-season break premiered last Monday. The episode was one hour long, but it was so packed with action that it only felt like five minutes. I was holding my breath and was on the edge of my seat the whole time. The story is approaching the start of Breaking Bad when we first see Saul in that show. There are only five episodes left and the show will be over in five weeks. I will be sad when this show ends :(</li>
<li>Volume 2 of <em>Stranger Things 4</em> came out on July 1. Unfortunately for me, some details of the ending were spoiled for me, but I enjoyed watching the show nonetheless.</li>
<li>Season 2 of <em>Only Murders in the Building</em> is going on. It is as intriguing as the first season. Steve Martin and Martin Short are an amazing duo.</li>
<li>The first two episodes of season 4 of <em>What We Do in the Shadows</em> premiered this Tuesday. Nadja, Nandor, Lazlo, and Gizmo are all reunited once again!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>I wrote a photopoem titled <em>rain train</em>. Here&rsquo;s the photo

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/rain-train.webp" alt="A train pulls into a station on a rainy day.">
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>

and <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/rain-train/">here&rsquo;s the poem →</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="some-fun-stuff-for-you">Some fun stuff for you</h2>
<h3 id="jwst-images">JWST images</h3>
<p>The first photographs taken by James Webb Space Telescope were released this week. They look beautiful. This one&rsquo;s my favourite:

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W28/webb.webp" alt="Carina nebula">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
        
            The Carina Nebula
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>

Check out the <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/webbfirstimages/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">full resolutions images on NASA&rsquo;s website →</a></p>
<h3 id="youtube-videos">YouTube videos</h3>
<p>Here are some YouTube videos that I watched and enjoyed recently:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the latest episode of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8q_05PUYv1o&amp;list=PLNYkxOF6rcIAKIQFsNbV0JDws_G_bnNo9" target="_blank" rel="noopener">HTTP 203</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9qen5CKjUe8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cassie Evans talks to Jake about about SVG paths</a> and what the various letters and symbols in an SVG file mean. The SVG format is similar to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtle_graphics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Turtle graphics</a> most commonly seen in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logo_%28programming_language%29" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Logo programming language</a>. I am loving the new episodes of HTTP 203, but this does not mean I don&rsquo;t miss Surma.</li>
<li>I used to <em>love</em> playing the Harry Potter games on PC. Which is why I was delighted when I found this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f-A2XlJsC84" target="_blank" rel="noopener">interview with Christo Vuchetich, a game designer who worked on the Harry Potter PC games</a>. It is incredible how the game was made in a year with very little access to how the Harry Potter movies would look like. An interview on the Chamber of Secrets game is coming soon.  I cannot wait to watch it.</li>
<li>The team at Polygon play a game of Clay-O-Rama which is like DnD, but the players make clay figurines of their characters. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AbEBGf1J_qw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Simone, Pat, and Christina play the game with Jenna as their DM</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B0dDjz9lDYQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Steve Carell talks about some moments and scenes from the Despicable Me and Minions movies</a>.</li>
<li>Fractals are beautiful! But what are they? <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ofFLYfUEPVE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Keenan Crane, a computer scientist from CMU, explains what are fractals in 5 different levels of difficulty</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="online-games">Online games</h3>
<p>You may enjoy playing these games:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Regular tic-tac-toe becomes boring after a while. If both players play optimally, then the game will end in a tie. I would like to introduce you to a bidding version of the same game. In regular tic-tac-toe, both players take turns alternatingly to place their respective symbol on the grid. In the bidding version, both players start with a limited fund of say 100 points. At the start of each turn, they both bid some points. The player with the higher bid gets to place their symbol on the grid but must pay their bid amount to the other player.</p>
<p>The players must not only decide where to place their symbol in their turn in case they win the bid, but they must also decide how much to bid. Should they go all in in the start and occupy a good starting square? Or should they save their points for the endgame to play several turns at one and deliver a deathblow? You can try it yourself and play with a friend on this website: <a href="http://biddingttt.herokuapp.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bidding TTT</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You might have played the game Wordle where you try to guess a word in 5 tries. You may like <a href="https://www.quordle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quordle</a> more. In this game, you are required to guess four words within nine guesses. In case this was not enough, you can try <a href="https://duotrigordle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Duotrigordle</a>. In this game, you must guess 32 words and you have 37 guesses to do so.  It was surprised to find that Duotrigordle was easier than Quordle.  Let me know which variant of Wordle is your favourite.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="two-songs">Two songs</h3>
<p>Here are two songs from Eurovision that you may enjoy:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Moskau</em> by Dschinghis Khan, Eurovision 1979<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i0xOSxgs6w8" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></li>
<li><em>Fairytale</em> by Alexander Rybek, Eurovision 2009<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WXwgZL4zx9o" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week! See you in the next one. 👋</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Stranger Things 4</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W23/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2022 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W23/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!</p>
<p>This week, I watched Volume 1 of Stranger Things 4, and it was some of the best content I have ever seen. I can&rsquo;t wait for the last two episodes of this season to land on July 1.</p>
<p>If you would like to read the previous issues, you can do so at <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter</a>.</p>
<h2 id="recent-updates">Recent updates</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s what&rsquo;s new with me:</p>
<ul>
<li>I shared a simple but tasty recipe of a <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/recipes/tomato-cheese-sandwich/">tomato cheese sandwich</a>.</li>
<li>It has started raining in Mumbai! The first showers of rain fell on Thursday. It reminds me of a photopoem I wrote last year titled <em>torrent</em>. Here&rsquo;s the photo

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W23/torrent.webp" alt="Raining at the Bandra-Worli sealink">
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>

and <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/torrent/">here&rsquo;s the poem →</a></li>
<li>I had gone to see the Gateway of India two weeks ago, and it looked pretty in purple.

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W23/gateway.webp" alt="Raining at the Bandra-Worli sealink">
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>

It looked like a gateway (get it? 😏) to the Upside Down.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="curated-content">Curated content</h2>
<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>
<p>I read a New Yorker article titled <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/06/13/the-strange-and-secret-ways-that-animals-perceive-the-world-ed-yong-immense-world-tom-mustill-how-to-speak-whale" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Strange and Secret Ways That Animals Perceive the World</a> by Elizabeth Kolbert. In this article, Kolbert talks about how there&rsquo;s so much that we don&rsquo;t know about animals: we don&rsquo;t know how they sense things, how they communicate with each other and with us. For instance, a researcher named Roger Payne found out about whale songs. He discovered that whales tend to repeat a sequence of sounds&ndash;that were 7 to 30 minutes long&ndash;over and over again. He thought of these as songs sung by the whales. He recorded this and released it as an album called &ldquo;Songs of the Humpback Whale&rdquo;. NASA even included these on Voyagers 1 and 2, which are now floating in space. Any alien that encounters these space probes will get a glimpse of what whales sound like. You can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sjkxUA041nM" target="_blank" rel="noopener">listen to these whale songs on YouTube</a>.</p>
<p>Related to this is another New Yorker article that I had read a while back: <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/04/05/why-animals-dont-get-lost" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Why Animals Don&rsquo;t Get Lost</a> by Kathryn Schulz. How do mammals, birds, and even insects such as butterflies navigate long distances and still reach at their intended destinations without the aid of a GPS? We are starting to understand this better with recent advancements in data collection, but there is still a long way to go. Both of these articles are humbling to read.</p>
<p>Speaking of whales, here&rsquo;s a news segment where Julianna McKannis asks a panel of experts: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=POi4rvN_Yts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Should we be teaching our children more about whales?</a></p>
<h3 id="youtube-videos">YouTube videos</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Shane of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/StuffMadeHere" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Stuff Made Here</a> posted the culmination of his Can&rsquo;t Miss basketball series. He uses maths, camera tracking and on-the-fly physics calculations to make sure that no matter how you throw the basketball, it goes in the hoop.
Follow his journey as he builds and improves his design and tackles more and more difficult challenges.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vtN4tkvcBMA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Part 1</a>: My curved basketball hoop always goes in.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FycDx69px8U" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Part 2</a>: Automatic hoop, unless you&rsquo;re my wife.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=myO8fxhDRW0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Part 3</a>: Moving hoop won&rsquo;t let you miss.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xHWXZyfhQas" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Part 4</a>: I made a 100MPH flying hoop.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kY8stpY4rrc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Millie Bobby Brown of Stranger Things play Box of Lies</a> with Jimmy Fallon on the Tonight Show.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RFcfJm3SqGk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Finn, Gaten, Priah, and Joseph from Stranger Things play a DnD adventure</a>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="songs-from-stranger-things">Songs from Stranger Things</h3>
<p>Here are some songs that were featured in Stranger Things 4.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EsyUa63NM1E" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Pass the Dutchie</em> by Musical Youth</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wp43OdtAAkM" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Running Up That Hill</em> by Kate Bush</a>. This song is topping the charts once again thanks to Stranger Things.</li>
<li><em>Never Ending Story</em> by Limahl: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2WN0T-Ee3q4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Here&rsquo;s the original version from 1984</a>, and here&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wE3fzo7xYv4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a rendition sung by Gaten and Gabriella</a> from the show.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week! See you in the next one.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>My weekly newsletter #2</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W22/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 14:22:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W22/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!
This is the second issue of my new newsletter, and it&rsquo;s the 22nd week of 2022.
Lots of two&rsquo;s this week!</p>
<p>In case you missed last week&rsquo;s issue, you can read it on my website at <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter</a>.</p>
<h2 id="whats-new-on-my-website">What&rsquo;s new on my website</h2>
<ul>
<li>It was Zero Shadow Day on May 15 in Mumbai. I <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/posts/zero-shadow-day/">wrote a post explaining what is “Zero Shadow Day”</a> and when you can expect to see it at your place.</li>
<li>I wrote a photopoem titled <em>high</em>. Here&rsquo;s the photo

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W22/high.webp" alt="Sun setting at the beach">
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>

and <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/high/">here&rsquo;s the poem →</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="whats-new-with-me">What&rsquo;s new with me</h2>
<ul>
<li>I finished reading <em>Crime and Punishment</em> by Fyodor Dostoevsky. It is a complex book that warrants a re-read. I will start reading <em>Anna Karenina</em> by Leo Tolstoy next.</li>
<li>I also finished reading <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/title-page.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Rust Book</a>. It is a great introduction to the Rust Programming Language and is a must-read for any aspiring Rustaceans.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="curated-content">Curated content</h2>
<p>Keeping with the theme of this issue, here are two of various things.</p>
<h3 id="two-youtube-videos">Two YouTube videos</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FJSI7QTAt_o" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tom Scott presents a game show titled Money</a>. In this show, five of Tom&rsquo;s YouTuber friends play for a piece of the potential prize pool of $10,000. They can win the entire amount as a group only if they work together and cooperate with each other. If someone defects and acts selfishly, the total winnings of the group falls.</p>
<p>This game is a test of trust, loyalty, and deceptiveness among the players. It is a great example of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Repeated_game" target="_blank" rel="noopener">repeated game</a> in action. Will the players cooperate, or will someone betray their friends for a chance to increase their personal winnings? Watch the show and find out!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In a web exclusive episode of Last Week Tonight, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hk011WMM7t0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John Oliver does an in-depth review of the 1997 movie Air Bud</a> which is about a dog that plays basketball. In this episode, he highlights and discusses the moral and ethical flaws of making a dog play professional basketball.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="two-websites">Two websites</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If you are tired of binging on Netflix and would like something more nutritional, check out <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NHK World-Japan</a>. This is the international broadcast service of NHK, a public broadcasting organisation in Japan.
There is a wide variety of shows and documentaries available <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/ondemand/video/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">On Demand</a> that you can watch for free without having to sign up.</p>
<p>A show that I liked was <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/ondemand/video/2068027/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Myths and Legends of Hiroshima and Shimane</a>. This show takes you on a train ride across towns in Hiroshima and Shimane, and gives a glimpse of the arts, the culture, the myths, and the legends on the way. Another show that I would like to watch is a <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/ondemand/program/video/10yearshayaomiyazaki/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">four-part documentary on Hayao Miyazaki</a>, the legendary Japanese filmmaker who co-founded Studio Ghibli.</p>
<p>If you are feeling nostalgic and miss the times when we all watched the same content at the same time and couldn&rsquo;t rewind or skip forward, there&rsquo;s <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/live/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Live TV</a> for you. There is also a section on the site where you can <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/nhkworld/en/learnjapanese/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">learn Japanese</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.redactle.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A fun game called Redactle</a> that you can play in your browser. In this game, you are given a Wikipedia article with almost all words redacted. You can guess a word, and if it is present in the article, then all occurences of the word are revealed. The objective of the game is to guess the title of the article.
While there is no limit on the number of words you can guess, you can set your own targets. I like to guess the title in the shortest time, so I don&rsquo;t care how many guesses it takes.</p>
<p>This game tests your general knowledge and pattern recognition skills. Having read a lot of Wikipedia articles certainly helps. A new article is available everyday at 9.30pm IST.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="two-excerpts">Two excerpts</h3>
<p>This first excerpt is from Crime and Punishment. It shows the thoughts of the main character Raskolnikov moments before he is about to commit a crime.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At first&mdash;even long before&mdash;he had been occupied with one question: why almost all crimes are so easily detected and solved, and why almost all criminals leave such an obviously marked trail. He came gradually to various and curious conclusions, the chief reason lying, in his opinion, not so much in the material impossibility of concealing the crime as in the criminal himself; the criminal himself, almost any criminal, experiences at the moment of the crime a sort of failure of will and reason, which on the contrary, are replaced by a phenomenal, childish thoughtlessness, just at the moment when reason and prudence are most necessary. According to his conviction, it turned out that this darkening of reason and failure will take hold of a man like a disease, develop gradually, and reach their height shortly before the crime is committed; they continue unabated during the moment of the crime itself and for some time after it, depending on the individual; then they pass in the same way as any disease passes. But the question whether the disease generates the crime, or the crime somehow by its peculiar nature is always accompanied by something akin to disease, he did not yet feel able to resolve.</p>
<p><cite>&ndash; Excerpt from Crime and Punishment by Fyodor Dostoevsky, translated by Richard Pevear and Larissa Volokhonsky
</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This second excerpt is much more light-hearted. It is a conversation that Mark Twain had while visiting Fiji in September:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;This? This is not hot. You ought to be here in the summer time once.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;We supposed that this was summer; it has the ear-marks of it. You could take it to almost any country and deceive people with it. But if it isn’t summer, what does it lack?&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It lacks half a year. This is mid-winter.&rdquo;</p>
<p><cite>&mdash; Excerpt from Following the Equator by Mark Twain</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="and-two-songs">and Two songs</h3>
<p>Here are two songs that have French names and were released in 1979:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Main dans la main</em> by Ellie et Jacno. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SolYdL5tcag" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></li>
<li><em>Voulez-Vous</em> by ABBA. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=za05HBtGsgU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week! See you in the next one.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Welcome to my Newsletter</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W21/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 16:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W21/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Hello there!</p>
<p>Welcome to my brand-new weekly newsletter.
Yes, I am starting a newsletter and this is the very first issue.
Each issue will include updates about what&rsquo;s new on this site and what&rsquo;s new with me.
I will also share links, quotes, music, videos, etc. that I encountered in the past week that I liked.
I hope you enjoy the newsletter and find it useful / interesting / fun!</p>
<p>I will upload a new issue every Saturday. You can sign up at <a href="http://newsletter.pranshugaba.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://newsletter.pranshugaba.com</a> and get the latest issue emailed straight to your inbox.
Alternatively, if you do not wish to share your email id, you could add the following feed to your favourite feed reader and you will be notified by your reader when a new issue is uploaded.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span class="line"><span class="cl">https://pranshugaba.com/newsletters/index.xml
</span></span></code></pre></div><p><a href="https://pranshugaba.com/subscribe/#feed-readers">Read more about using feed readers →</a></p>
<p>All issues will also be available on my website at <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/">https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter</a>. You can bookmark this page and browse through it anytime you like.</p>
<h2 id="whats-new-on-my-site">What&rsquo;s new on my site</h2>
<ul>
<li>I shared <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/minis/9/">a picture of the Gateway of India</a> which was lit up beautifully on Thursday.</li>
<li>I wrote a photopoem called <em>sunset</em>.

<figure class="medium">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/newsletter/2022-W21/sunset.webp" alt="Sun setting at the beach">
    </picture>
    
    
</figure>

<a href="https://pranshugaba.com/poems/sunset/">Read the accompanying poem →</a></li>
<li>I wrote this issue of the newsletter, and set up my website to be able to add more issues! (sorry, this is getting meta&hellip;)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="whats-new-with-me">What&rsquo;s new with me</h2>
<ul>
<li>My batchmates from TIFR and I are conducting a Chai and Why session on <time datetime="2022-05-29T11:00:00+05:30">Sunday, May 29 (tomorrow) at 11 am</time>. It will be an hour-long interactive session where we explore puzzles related to graph theory. The venue is <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/way/978614999" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ruparel College, Matunga West, Mumbai</a>. You can drop by if you are around, or you can <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qakLY2e_YMo" target="_blank" rel="noopener">watch it live on YouTube</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://pranshugaba.com/minis/7/">I went to a book fair</a> and bought some books by weight, and then <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/minis/8/">went to a book store</a> and bought some more books.</li>
<li>I started playing the overwhelmingly positively rated puzzle game <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baba_Is_You" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Baba is You</em></a>. I have only played the first 15 levels, but the concept is amazing and I have never seen anything like it before. In this game, you move around blocks to change the rules of the game to be able to clear each level. It&rsquo;s brilliant.</li>
<li>I began reading <em>Following the Equator</em> by Mark Twain. It is humorous and informative. You will find an excerpt from the book below. <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/reads/">Also see my reading list →</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="curated-content">Curated content</h2>
<p>Here are some titbits that I found this week that you might enjoy.</p>
<h3 id="some-youtube-videos">Some YouTube videos</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=twAP3buj9Og" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Who made these circles in the Sahara?</a> is an excellent video by Vox. Inspired by a peculiar observation made by a Redditor while browsing Google Earth, <a href="https://www.vox.com/authors/christophe-haubursin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Christophe Hausbursin</a> leads an investigation trying to solve the mystery behind the mysterious circles seen in the Saharan desert.</li>
<li>Two Ryan Georges discuss <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cwu1rCjb1Fk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">how the traps and riddles around ancient relics were designed</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o54sGWJd8tg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joel Haver has fun standing on a pile of rocks</a>, even though it&rsquo;s not safe.</li>
<li>And finally, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_v89pVOW2aE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a joke by Norm MacDonald</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="a-song">A song</h3>
<p><em>Numb Little Bug</em> by Em Beihold<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fwJ8H5wWCU" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch on YouTube →</a></p>
<h3 id="and-an-excerpt">And an excerpt</h3>
<p>Mark Twain&rsquo;s take on crossing the International Date Line:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sept. 8.&mdash;Sunday. We are moving so nearly south that we cross only about two meridians of longitude a day. This morning we were in longitude 178 west from Greenwich, and 57 degrees west from San Francisco. To-morrow we shall be close to the center of the globe&mdash;the 180th degree of west longitude and 180th degree of east longitude.</p>
<p>And then we must drop out a day&mdash;lose a day out of our lives, a day never to be found again. We shall all die one day earlier than from the beginning of time we were foreordained to die. We shall be a day behindhand all through eternity. We shall always be saying to the other angels, &ldquo;Fine day today,&rdquo; and they will be always retorting, &ldquo;But it isn&rsquo;t to-day, it&rsquo;s tomorrow.&rdquo; We shall be in a state of confusion all the time and shall never know what true happiness is.</p>
<p><cite>&mdash; Excerpt from <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/2895/2895-h/2895-h.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Following the Equator</em>, by Mark Twain</a></cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for this week! See you in the next one.</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>