<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Articles by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/</link><description>Interesting things, websites, places, etc.</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 17:43:06 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Wellbeing in GNOME 48</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/wellbeing-in-gnome-48/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 12:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/wellbeing-in-gnome-48/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>I <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/uses/">use</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fedora_Linux" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Fedora Linux</a> with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNOME_Shell" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GNOME desktop environment</a> on all of my computers.
<a href="https://fedoramagazine.org/announcing-fedora-linux-42/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A new version of Fedora (42, yay!)</a> was released recently, and with it came <a href="https://release.gnome.org/48/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a new version of GNOME (48)</a>.
Each GNOME release is named after a city, and GNOME 48 is named &ldquo;Bengaluru&rdquo;, a city that I lived in for four years and absolutely love.</p>
<p>GNOME 48 is not a major update, but it comes with several quality-of-life improvements.
While many of the features new to GNOME 48 already exist in some form in other desktop environments and/or operating systems, it is great to see them included in GNOME.</p>
<ul>
<li>Multiple notifications from the same application now stack. This reduces clutter and makes the notification panel better organised.</li>
<li>You can now limit charging your device to 80%. This reduces the strain on your battery and will improve the battery health in the long run, especially if you keep your laptop plugged in all day.</li>
<li>The default interface font was changed from Cantarell to Adwaita Sans, a modified version of <a href="https://rsms.me/inter/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Inter</a>. I love how Inter looks. In fact, I use Inter widely across my site.</li>
<li>My favourite new feature in GNOME 48 is <em>Wellbeing</em>, which gives you screen time information and regular eyesight and movement break reminders.</li>
</ul>

<figure class="gnome-screenshot">
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <source srcset="https://pranshugaba.com/articles/wellbeing-in-gnome-48/wellbeing-dark.webp" media="(prefers-color-scheme: dark)">
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/articles/wellbeing-in-gnome-48/wellbeing-light.webp" alt="The wellbeing interface in GNOME settings.">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            The wellbeing interface in GNOME settings.
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>With Screen Time, I can now track how long I use my devices each day.
It also gives me the option to limit the usage in a day, after which the screen turns greyscale.
I have set the daily limit to be 8 hours, which while generous, helps me limit the time spent in front of the screen.
The Screen Time feature in macOS is more advanced:
it has features such as focus modes, time tracking on a per-app basis, and syncing usage data across devices.
While I would love to see some of these features included in GNOME, I am still happy with the simple implementation that we currently have.</p>
<p>I find the break reminders in GNOME very useful.
When I am working, it is very easy for me to become engrossed in my work and spend hours at a stretch staring at the screen without moving.
Break reminders remind me every once in a while to take a break.
The screen dims and a notification appears, telling me what to do.</p>
<ul>
<li>Eyesight reminders tell me to look away from the screen, into the distance, for about 20 seconds.
This gives my eyes some much needed rest.</li>
<li>Movement reminders tell me to get up and move around for a while. I take movement breaks for five minutes every thirty minutes.
During the break, I get up, move around the room, stretch my body, and do some light workout.
I also finish up small tasks such as organising my desk and my room, and refilling my water bottle.
In some breaks, I simply stare out of the window and think about how I want to spend the next 25 minutes.</li>
</ul>
<p>When these breaks end, there is an audible ding, indicating that it is time to resume work.
I have found that taking these short breaks immensely improve my wellbeing, just as the name of the feature suggests.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Of Mice and Men</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/of-mice-and-men/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 23:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/of-mice-and-men/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>I came across an old hardbound copy of <em>Of Mice and Men</em> in the librerie<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> at TIFR.
The title seemed familiar and intriguing, the quality of the hardbound was excellent, and the golden ochre pages had the mesmerising old paper smell:
it was hard not to pick this book up.
It is a short and captivating read and I finished it in a few days.
I liked it so much that I wanted to share my thoughts on it here.</p>


<aside class="[ toc ] [ plain-link border-medium border-radius-large ]">
  <details >
    <summary>
      <h2 class="toc__heading">Table of Contents</h2>
    </summary>
    <nav id="TableOfContents">
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#spoiler-free-review">Spoiler-free review</a></li>
    <li><a href="#review-with-spoilers">Review with spoilers</a>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="#george-and-lennie">George and Lennie</a></li>
        <li><a href="#petting-and-rabbits">Petting and rabbits</a></li>
        <li><a href="#the-characters">The characters</a></li>
        <li><a href="#dreaming-of-a-better-future">Dreaming of a better future</a></li>
        <li><a href="#the-people-are-all-on-their-own">The people are all on their own</a></li>
        <li><a href="#cyclical-story-and-foreshadowing">Cyclical story and foreshadowing</a></li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ul>
</nav>
  </details>
</aside>

<h2 id="spoiler-free-review">Spoiler-free review</h2>
<p>The book is primarily a tale of two men: George Milton (who is small and witty) and Lennie Small (who is slow and brawny).
The story takes place along the Salinas river near the Gabilan mountains, a few miles south of Soledad, California.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>
The two men are going to go work on a ranch to buck barley, and this is where they (and the reader) meet a slew of characters.
There are conflicts in no time, and the story gets tense quickly.
I go into more detail on this in the <a href="#review-with-spoilers">spoiler section of the review</a>.</p>
<p>The plot is well-paced, well-written, and there is always some action taking place.
It is simple, and yet, it keeps you hooked.
There is vivid description of nature and the passage of time, which helps set the scene and the setting of rural America.</p>
<ul>
<li>&ldquo;The day was going fast now. Only the tops of the Gabilan Mountains flamed with the light of the sun that had gone from the valley.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;The flame of the sunset lifted from the mountatintops and dusk came into the valley&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Now the light was lifting as the sun went down, and the sun streaks climbed up the wall and fell over the feeding racks and over the heads of the horses.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;The sun streaks were high on the wall by now, and the light was growing soft in the barn.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Already the sun had left the valley to go climbing up the slopes of the Gabilan Mountains, and the hilltops were rosy in the sun.&rdquo;</li>
<li>&ldquo;Only the topmost ridges were in the sun now.&rdquo;</li>
</ul>
<p>Also contributing to the tone is the grammar of the dialogue of the characters.
The characters speak with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_negative" target="_blank" rel="noopener">negative concord</a>, that is, they use double negatives even when they want to make a negative statement.
They also use words and phrases such as &ldquo;sets&rdquo; and &ldquo;could of&rdquo; and &ldquo;ast&rdquo; and &ldquo;purty&rdquo; and &ldquo;pitchers&rdquo;.
It didn&rsquo;t take long for me to understand what the characters were saying.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>
It was fun to read this dialogue as it made the characters real and believable.</p>
<p>I loved reading this novella!
I suggest that you read the book before proceeding further to the section with spoilers so as to not deprive yourself of the opportunity to experience this story.</p>
<h2 id="review-with-spoilers">Review with spoilers</h2>



<aside class="admonition warning">
    <div class="admonition__title">
        Warning
    </div>
	<div class="admonition__content">
        <p>Spoilers for the plot of <em>Of Mice and Men</em> up ahead.</p>

    </div>
</aside>
<h3 id="george-and-lennie">George and Lennie</h3>
<p><em>Of Mice and Men</em> is a tragedy concerning many men, a woman, and hardly any mice.
The story is set in a world where each man is on his own, and in this setting, the two protagonists are an unlikely duo who always stick together.
The two men could not be more different.
George knows how to talk to people, and how to get out and stay out of trouble, whereas Lennie gets heavy physical labour done like it&rsquo;s a piece of cake.
George wishes he would not have to take care of Lennie all the time, and that he would be better off alone.
However, he knows that this is not true.
George cares for Lenny, and Lenny cares for George as well.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;He ain&rsquo;t no cuckoo,&rdquo; said George. &ldquo;He&rsquo;s dumb as hell, but he ain&rsquo;t crazy. An&rsquo; I ain&rsquo;t so bright neither, or I wouldn&rsquo;t be buckin&rsquo; barley for my fifty and found. If I was bright, if I was even a little bit smart, I&rsquo;d have my own little place, an&rsquo; I&rsquo;d be bringin&rsquo; in my own crops, &lsquo;stead of doin&rsquo; all the work and not getting what comes up outa the ground.&rdquo;
<cite>&mdash; George speaks of Lennie</cite></p></blockquote>
<h3 id="petting-and-rabbits">Petting and rabbits</h3>
<p>Lennie does not remember things well.
Lennie forgets most things.
George has to constantly keep reminding him of what events took place recently, and this also tells us what happened.
We learn two crucial points at the start of the story: we learn that something bad happened in Weed, which is why they were on the lam, and that Lennie loves to pet mice.
Lennie loves petting all things (especially mice), but since he is so big and strong, he inadvertently kills the mice.
Lennie is deeply interested in is rabbits.
He wants a simple life, and he would like nothing better than to pet animals.
And he likes rabbits better than mice because they are larger, and he could pet them harder without killing them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;I never meant no harm, George. Honest I never.&rdquo;
<cite>&mdash; Lennie</cite></p></blockquote>
<p>Lennie is like a big baby.
His actions are cruel, but his intentions are not.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Sure he&rsquo;s jes&rsquo; like a kid. There ain&rsquo;t no more harm in him than a kid neither, except he&rsquo;s so strong.&rdquo;
[&hellip;]
&ldquo;He&rsquo;s a nice fella,&rdquo; said Slim. &ldquo;Guy don&rsquo;t need no sense to be a nice fella. Seems to me sometimes it jus&rsquo; works the other way around. Take a real smart guy and he ain&rsquo;t hardly ever a nice fella.&rdquo;
<cite>&mdash; Slim speaks of Lennie</cite></p></blockquote>
<h3 id="the-characters">The characters</h3>
<p>As the pair reach their new workplace, we meet a bunch of new characters.
We are introduced to Candy, an old swamper, who lost his arm in an accident at the ranch.
We also briefly see the boss, the owner of the ranch.
There is Curley, the son of the owner who is always looking to cause trouble, and there is Curley&rsquo;s wife, who got married to Curley just two weeks ago.
In addition, we also come across Slim, Carlson, Whit, and other workers.
Finally, we also hear of Crooks, a person of color who is the stable buck.</p>
<h3 id="dreaming-of-a-better-future">Dreaming of a better future</h3>
<p>George is focussed on getting their own land, their own mansion.
This idea seems grandiose to everyone else, no one believes that this can succeed.
No one except George and Lennie (and later Candy).
George has told this story to Lennie so many times that they (even Lennie!) remember it by heart.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>George&rsquo;s voice became deeper. He repeated his rhythmically as though he had said them many times before. &ldquo;Guys like us, that work on ranches, are the loneliest guys in the world. They got no family. They don&rsquo;t belong no place. They come to a ranch an&rsquo; work up a stake and then they go inta town and blow their stake, and the first thing you know they&rsquo;re poundin&rsquo; their tail on some other ranch. They ain&rsquo;t got nothing to look ahead to.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;<em>An&rsquo; live off the fatta the lan&rsquo;</em>,&rdquo; Lennie shouted.</p></blockquote>
<p>George is cunning, he knows ways to help him achieve his goal.
For example, when he learns from Candy that they will get money for their stake if there is an accident on the ranch, he orchestrates and instigates a fight between Curley and Lennie, knowing all well that Lennie will hurt Curley, and that Lennie may get hurt too.
At the end, they manage to extract compensation from Curley.</p>
<p>They were on their way to earn enough money for the stake.
Unfortunately, as it turned out, the events at the end of the book made it impossible for their dream to come as it turns out.</p>
<h3 id="the-people-are-all-on-their-own">The people are all on their own</h3>
<p>A recurring motif throughout the book is that everyone is either alone or ends up alone.</p>
<p>Carlson insists that they kill Candy&rsquo;s old dog.
They say that Candy&rsquo;s dog is old and of no use, and stinks, and has rheumatism.
However, Candy loves and values his dog.
After all, they have grown up together.
Carlson suggests to shoot the dog in the back of the head with his Luger pistol.</p>
<p>We see that Crooks is alone as he is a &ldquo;colored man&rdquo;.
It is only Lennie, who does not have any of the inhibitions or prejudices against Crooks because of race, who talks to him.</p>
<p>We see that no one speaks to Curley&rsquo;s wife, for she is a woman.
What&rsquo;s worse is that she remains an unnamed character throughout the book; Steinbeck does not even give her a name.</p>
<p>In the climax of the story, Lennie means no harm, but ends up killing a pup, and then kills Curley&rsquo;s wife as well.
Candy is the first to find out, and George finds out too soon thereafter.
George knows that Curley and others will not like what George did.
This is a repeat of the Weed incident all over again, but even worse this time.
George tries to convince Curley and Carlson to let Lennie live, but they do not listen.
He has no choice but to go along with the others.</p>
<p>We cut to Lennie in his safe spot, as instructed by George.
George leads the rest of the gang to Lennie.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;I ain&rsquo;t got no people,&rdquo; George said. &ldquo;I seen the guys that go around on the ranches alone. That ain&rsquo;t no good.  They don&rsquo;t have no fun. After a long time they get mean. They get wantin&rsquo; to fight all the time.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Ain&rsquo;t many guys travel around together,&rdquo; he mused &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know why. Maybe ever&rsquo;body in the whole damn world is scared of each other.&rdquo;</p>
<p>&ldquo;It&rsquo;s a lot nice to go around with a guy you know,&rdquo; said George.</p></blockquote>
<h3 id="cyclical-story-and-foreshadowing">Cyclical story and foreshadowing</h3>
<p>The story is cyclical in nature.
The book begins near a pool, with sycamore trees, and a heron, and both men walking towards the pool, and Lennie has done something bad, unintentionally.
The book ends with all of these conditions.
I half expected the book to end as it started, showing a recurring loop.
However, what happens is much darker.</p>
<p>George ends up killing Lennie.
He talks to Lennie about their dream one final time, and then shoots him in the back of his neck with the Luger, just how Candy&rsquo;s dog died.
The only difference being, that it was George himself who killed his &lsquo;dog&rsquo; unlike Candy.</p>
<p>I feel terrible for Lennie.
Lennie died even though he didn&rsquo;t mean any harm.
In some ways, it was a worse ending for George, as he has to live with the fact that he killed his friend, and now he ends up alone, just like everyone else.</p>



<aside class="admonition book-info">
    <div class="admonition__title">
        Book info
    </div>
	<div class="admonition__content">
        <p>Author: John Steinbeck<br>
Number of Pages: 186<br>
Publisher: The Modern Library<br>
Published: 1938<br>
Language: English<br>
Illustrations: No</p>

    </div>
</aside>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A <em>librerie</em> is a public bookshelf in TIFR where anyone can freely keep and take books.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>I learned from the author bio, and later from the introduction, that Steinbeck was born in Salinas where the story is set.
My edition had an introduction by Joseph Henry Jackson where he talked about the life and the personality of Steinbeck.
As a general rule, I never read the introduction before reading the main text since it is often riddled with spoilers for the story, or with thoughts and trivia about the author&rsquo;s life.
I like to go in a book blind and not be affected by such additional information, and come back to it only after I have finished reading the book.
The only time when this rule failed me was in <em>Lolita</em>, where the introduction is in fact diegetic.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>&ldquo;sets&rdquo; means &ldquo;sits&rdquo;, &ldquo;could of&rdquo; means &ldquo;could have&rdquo;, &ldquo;ast&rdquo; is &ldquo;asked&rdquo;, &ldquo;purty&rdquo; is &ldquo;pretty&rdquo;, &ldquo;pitchers&rdquo; is &ldquo;pitchers&rdquo;.&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description></item><item><title>On commence...</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/on-commence/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 20:00:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/on-commence/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Bonjour à tous !
Comment ça va ?
Bien, j&rsquo;espère.</p>
<p>Il y a quelques temps, j&rsquo;ai commencé à apprendre le français, et j&rsquo;aimerais le pratiquer.
En fait, j’avais appris du français en école, mais j&rsquo;ai presque tout oublié.
Alors, j&rsquo;écrirai une nouvelle chaque semaine, ici sur mon site.</p>
<p>D&rsquo;abord, je me présente.
Je m&rsquo;appelle Pranshu.
J&rsquo;ai 25 ans.
Je suis étudiant et chercheur à «Tata Institute of Fundamental Research», où je suis en quatrième année.
J&rsquo;étudie l&rsquo;informatique théorique, des méthodes formelles.
Plus précisément, je travaille sur la théorie de logique, automates et jeux.</p>
<p>L&rsquo;université est située en Colaba, le plus au sud de Mumbai.
Elle est très jolie.
Elle donne sur la mer et l&rsquo;on peut voir les bâtiments à Malabar.
J&rsquo;adore regarder le ciel orange et le coucher de soleil tous les soirs.
L&rsquo;université est au milieu d&rsquo;une zone navale, donc, il y a très peu de choses à faire près d&rsquo;ici.
Cependant, il y a beaucoup de restaurants et sites touristiques à Fort, à seulement vingt minutes d&rsquo;ici en bus.
Par exemple, il y a la porte de l&rsquo;Inde, le musée et des galeries d&rsquo;art.
J&rsquo;aime bien mon université !</p>
<p>Alors, c&rsquo;est tout pour aujourd&rsquo;hui.
Je vous souhaite une bonne semaine.
À la prochaine !</p>
<hr>
<p>Si vous trouvez des erreurs dans ce texte, n&rsquo;hésitez pas à <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/contact/">me contacter</a>.
J&rsquo;apprends le français et je fais des fautes.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>SoME #2</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/some-2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/some-2/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<h2 id="last-year">Last year</h2>
<p>Last summer, <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Grant Sanderson of 3Blue1Brown</a> held a contest named SoME #1. The name is short for <em>The Summer of Math Exposition</em>. In this contest, Grant asked people to submit maths explainers &mdash; something that explains a concept in maths (or physics or computer science). This explainer could be of any form: a short video, a blog post, an interactive webpage, or even a game! The goal of this contest was to encourage more people to create explainers.</p>
<p>There are multiple benefits to this. One, it improves the collection of resources available to all for learning new things (More than a 1000 entries were submitted!). Everyone has a different learning style, and similarly, everyone has a different teaching style. Even if someone has made a video explaining a particular concept, the way you explain the same topic will be different. Some people will find their content easier to understand, and some will find your content easier to understand. The more high-quality content there is out there, the higher the chance that you will find something that you can connect to.</p>
<p>Secondly, when you explain a concept to someone else, you tend to dispel misconceptions you may have had about the topic, and you might find an easier way of thinking about a problem as you try to present it in a simple manner for the explainer. You are bound to learn something new and improve your own understanding of the subject. It is a win-win-win for everybody!</p>
<p>You can <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/blog/some1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">read more about last year&rsquo;s contest on Grant&rsquo;s website</a>.
You can also find <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/blog/some1-results#all-entries" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a list of all submitted entries</a> there. You can read/watch them at your leisure and learn many things new.</p>
<h2 id="this-year">This year</h2>
<p>The #1 in SoME #1 suggested that this could be a recurring event, and sure enough, it&rsquo;s back this year as SoME #2.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hZuYICAEN9Y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Watch the announcement video by Grant on YouTube →</a></p>
<p>Not much has changed from last year.
This time, there is an additional platform to help domain experts to collaborate with content producers.
A repository has been setup on GitHub to help people with complementary skills to find and connect with each other.</p>
<p>For example, say you are well-versed in topology and would like to make a game related to something in topology, but don&rsquo;t know how to make games. You can request for a game developer on the GitHub page. Similarly, if you are good at making videos but don&rsquo;t know what to make the video about, you can look for a domain expert who would like to get a video made. By collaborating with others, you can make something amazing, something that would be impossible working on your own.</p>
<p>Here are some important links for this year&rsquo;s SoME:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://summerofmathexposition.substack.com/p/the-summer-of-math-exposition-is" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contest rules and details</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/leios/SoME_Topics/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GitHub for collaboration and matchmaking</a></li>
<li><a href="https://discord.gg/dsp3zgB4qQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Discord for general discussion</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfeYb0k8wr14WkMWYaeYpw6iiygOqA-Jwi_YMNPgRVJzMPOoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submission form</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The deadline for submitting your work is 15th August 2022.
Five winners will be selected who each will be awarded a Golden Pi creature and a prize money of $1000 sponsored by Brilliant. Very exciting!</p>
<p>I will not have time to make a video this year, but I will write a series on the <em>Determinacy of Two-player Games with Perfect Information</em>. The topic is inspired by some papers that I recently read that were written by Gale and Stewart and by Donald Martin. I will upload the series on this site.</p>
<p>Good luck! I hope you make some awesome maths explainers!</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Zero Shadow Day</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/zero-shadow-day/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 12:35:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/zero-shadow-day/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>When the clock strikes twelve during the day, we say it&rsquo;s noon. We may perceive this to be the time when the Sun is at its highest point in the sky. However, this is rarely, if ever, true.</p>
<p>To avoid confusion, let&rsquo;s say when the clock reads 12:00, it is <em>noon</em>, and when the Sun is at its highest, it is <em>local noon</em>. It will soon be clear why it&rsquo;s called it local noon.</p>
<h2 id="why-is-noon-not-the-same-as-local-noon">Why is noon not the same as local noon?</h2>
<p>The earth rotates about its axis, making a complete turn every 24 hours. Because of this, we see the Sun rise and set every day. The Earth rotates from west to east, so the Sun appears to rise in the east and set in the west.</p>
<p>Places that are in the east experience events like sunrise and sunset before places in the west. Consider Mumbai and Pune, two cities in Maharashtra, India. Because Pune is roughly 1 degree east of Mumbai, the day begins and ends in Pune slightly earlier than it does in Mumbai. We can calculate how much earlier:</p>
<p>The Earth rotates about 360 degrees in 24 hours<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. Dividing 24 hours by 360 tells us that the Earth rotates 1 degree in 4 minutes. It follows that local noon in Pune is 4 minutes before local noon in Mumbai. You can find out the sunrise and sunset times in these two cities and verify that these events occur 4 minutes earlier in Pune compared to Mumbai.</p>
<p>India is a big country; it is the seventh largest in the world by area. It spans about 30 degrees from west to east. The westernmost point of India is Sir Creek, Gujarat at 68 degrees east of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prime_meridian" target="_blank" rel="noopener">prime meridian</a> (the meridian that passes through Greenwich, London and is taken to be the zero longitude), and the easternmost point of India is in Arunachal Pradesh at 97.5 degrees east of the prime meridian. As a result, Arunachal Pradesh is about 2 hours ahead of Gujarat. Indeed, local noon is at 10:27 AM in Arunachal Pradesh and at 12:24 PM in Gujarat today.</p>
<p>Since all of India follows the same timezone (Indian Standard Time UTC+05:30), it follows that local noon does not occur at noon in most places.
The time at which local noon occurs at a place depends on the difference between the longitude of that place and the longitude corresponding to the timezone offset of that place.</p>
<p>In particular, given the timezone offset and the longitude of a place, the following formula calculates when local noon occurs there:
</p>
\[LN(z, \ell) = \left( \frac{z}{24}  - \frac{\ell}{360} \right) \times 24 \times 60\]<p>
Here,</p>
<ul>
<li>\(z\) is the timezone offset of the place. It is the number of hours the local timezone is ahead of UTC. It is a number between -12 and +12.</li>
<li>\(\ell\) is the longitude of the place. It must be a number between -180 and +180.</li>
<li>\(LN(z, \ell)\) is the number of minutes after 12:00 that local noon occurs at. If this value is negative, then local noon occurs before 12:00.</li>
</ul>
<p>We can look at an example. The timezone in Mumbai is +5:30, so we have \(z_{\text{Mumbai}} = 5.5\). The longitude of Mumbai is 72.8 degrees east, therefore, \(l_{\text{Mumbai}} = 72.8\). Substituting these values in the above formula gives
</p>
\[ LN(5.5, 72.8) = \left( \frac{5.5}{24} - \frac{72.8}{360} \right) \times 24 \times 60,\]<p>
which is approximately equal to 38. This tells us that local noon in Mumbai should be around 12:38 PM.</p>
<p>Why does this formula work? The difference in the parentheses indicates a fraction of Earth&rsquo;s complete rotation. The term \(\frac{z}{24}\) is the fraction of a rotation that timezone is ahead of UTC, and \(\frac{\ell}{360}\) is the fraction of a rotation that the longitude is ahead of the prime meridian.
The difference shows the fraction of a turn that Earth must rotate for the longitude of the place to reach the longitude corresponding to the timezone of the place.</p>
<p>We multiply this difference by \(24 \times 60\) to convert the fraction into minutes (since there are \(24 \times 60\) minutes in a day). This formula also agrees with the observation we made: the further east you go in the same timezone, the earlier local noon occurs.</p>
<p>The formula makes one assumption. It assumes that if the difference \(\frac{z}{24} - \frac{\ell}{360}\) at a place is zero, then \(LN(z, \ell)\) is also zero there, and local noon coincides with noon.
Is this a valid assumption to make?</p>
<p>For every timezone, there exists a longitude for which this difference is zero. We call this the longitude corresponding to the timezone, and it is equal to \(\frac{z}{24} \times 360\).
For example, the longitude corresponding to the Indian timezone is
</p>
\[\frac{5.5}{24} \times 360,\]<p>
which is equal to \(82.5^{\circ} \text{E}\).
The city of Vindhyachal in Uttar Pradesh, India lies on the 82.5 degrees east meridian.
Is it true that local noon is at 12:00 everyday in Vindhyachal?
Equivalently, is local noon in Mumbai at 12.38 PM everyday?
The answer to these questions is no, it&rsquo;s not that simple.</p>
<h3 id="local-noon-also-depends-on-the-time-of-the-year">Local noon also depends on the time of the year</h3>
<p>It turns out that local noon at a place changes from day to day across the year. In Mumbai, it ranges between 12.10 PM and 12.40 PM over the course of the year.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>
Why does this happen?</p>
<p>The answer has got to do with the eccentricity of Earth&rsquo;s orbit. The orbit of the Earth is not perfectly circular, but is slightly squished. Kepler found out that Earth&rsquo;s orbit is elliptical with the Sun at one of the ellipse&rsquo;s foci. The distance between the Earth and the Sun increases and decreases over the course of a year. Kepler also observed that the line joining the Earth and the Sun, the area that it sweeps per unit time is constant and is independent of where Earth is on the ellipse. Therefore, when the Earth is closer to the Sun, it moves faster, and when it is further away, it moves slower.</p>
<p>This means that the time between two consecutive local noons at a place is not always 24 hours. When the Earth is closer to the Sun and it moves faster, after it makes one complete rotation, it overshoots the sun by a greater amount, and thus must rotate by a greater angle for it to be local noon again. The gap between two local noons is longer. Conversely, when the Earth is further from the Sun and it is moving slowly, it overshoots the Sun by a smaller amount, and must rotate by a smaller angle for the Sun to become overhead again. Local noons are closer together during this time.</p>
<p>It would be quite inconvenient if the length of the day was different everyday, and some days of the year were shorter than others. The solution that people came up with was to take the average length of the day and have the day be that long every day. We took the total time duration of the year, and divided it into 365 equal parts (366 in leap years). This way, every day is 24 hours long.
The downside of this approach is that local noon time changes from day to day, but that&rsquo;s not an issue for most of us.</p>
<h2 id="shadow-length-at-local-noon">Shadow length at local noon</h2>
<p>Okay, so say you have found out the time of local noon at your place today. In Mumbai, it is at 12.20 PM today.
At local noon, the Sun would be overhead, the highest it will ever be in the day, and this is the time of the day when your shadow will be the shortest.
Does this necessarily mean that your shadow will be exactly below your feet and therefore, not visible at all? The answer is no, you will still be able to see a shadow of yourself in most places.</p>
<p>At any time, there is a meridian &mdash; a semicircle joining the north and the south poles on the surface of the Earth &mdash; where it is local noon.
This &ldquo;meridian of local noon&rdquo; constantly shifts west as the Earth rotates about its axis.
This is the meridian passing through the point on Earth that is closest to the Sun.
You can convince yourself that the closest point is also the unique point on Earth&rsquo;s surface that lies on the line segment joining the centres of the Earth and the Sun. This point is also known as the subsolar point of Earth.</p>
<p>If you are on the meridian where it&rsquo;s currently local noon, then the Sun would be neither east nor west. You would see that your shadow has no component in the east-west direction.</p>
<p>Furthermore, if you are at the point that is closest to the sun, then the Sun be exactly overhead above you, and your shadow will not have any component in the north-south direction either. For a moment, you will experience the &ldquo;Zero Shadow&rdquo; effect. Shadows of objects would be exactly below them giving the illusion that they don&rsquo;t have shadows at all.
Things looks surreal; it feels like you are in a video game where the shadows did not render.</p>
<p>At all other points on the &ldquo;meridian of local noon&rdquo;, the Sun will be to the north or south depending on whether you are to the south or the north of the subsolar point. Any object will cast a shadow in the north-south direction even at local noon.</p>
<h2 id="latitudes-where-zero-shadow-is-observed">Latitudes where Zero Shadow is observed</h2>
<p>The Earth rotates about its axis and revolves around the Sun. If the Earth&rsquo;s axis was perpendicular to the plane of Earth&rsquo;s orbit, then at any given time, the location on Earth closest to the Sun would lie on the Equator. Only places on the equator would experience Zero Shadow (and they would do so everyday) and no other latitude would ever experience the Zero Shadow effect.</p>
<p>However, Earth&rsquo;s axis is not perpendicular to plane of Earth&rsquo;s orbit. Earth&rsquo;s axis makes an angle of 23.5 degrees with the plane of Earth&rsquo;s orbit. Because of this, the latitude of the subsolar point moves between 23.5 degrees north and 23.5 degrees south through the course of a year. These latitudes are also known as Tropic of Cancer and Tropic of Capricorn respectively.</p>
<p>On the summer solstice (June 21), the subsolar point lies on the Tropic of Cancer (23.5 degrees north), and on the winter solstice (December 21), the subsolar point lies on the Tropic of Capricorn (23.5 degrees south). Throughout the rest of the year, the latitude of Zero Shadow moves between the tropics.</p>
<p>The day when Zero Shadow is observed at a place is called &ldquo;Zero Shadow Day&rdquo;.
All places that lie between the Tropic of Cancer and Tropic of Capricorn experience Zero Shadow Day twice a year.
The tropics observe Zero Shadow Day only once a year. The Tropic of Cancer sees Zero Shadow Day on the summer solstice and the Tropic of Capricorn sees it on the winter solstice.
Places outside the tropics never observe Zero Shadow Day as the Sun can never be overhead those places.</p>
<h3 id="zero-shadow-day-in-mumbai">Zero Shadow Day in Mumbai</h3>
<p>I stay in Mumbai, which is at latitude \(19.1^{\circ} \text{N} \). At this latitude, the Zero Shadow Days are 15 May and 28 August.
Around local noon, (which happens to be around 12.20 PM), if it is sunny, we will get to experience Zero Shadow.</p>
<p>It usually rains in Mumbai in August. The sky is covered with grey clouds which diffuse the sunlight, and objects don&rsquo;t have distinct shadows. In a way, this is also &ldquo;Zero Shadow&rdquo;, but there is no interesting astronomical phenomenon at play here.</p>
<h3 id="zero-shadow-day-at-your-location">Zero Shadow Day at your location</h3>
<p><a href="https://alokm.com/zsd.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">This site by Alok Mandavgane</a> shows the Zero Shadow Days of any place on Earth. You can double click on a point on a map to see which days are Zero Shadow Days there.
<a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.alokm.zsd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">They have made an Android app</a> as well that you can play with.</p>
<h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading</h2>
<p>When, if at all, are the Zero Shadow Days at your place? Click some pictures on Zero Shadow Day and share them!
If you liked this post, <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/contact/">let me know</a> and share it with your friends.
It encourages me to write more.</p>
<p>If you found this topic interesting and would like to read more about it, here are some links for you:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equation_of_time" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Equation of Time</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sundial" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sundials</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subsolar_point" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Subsolar point</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Actually, the Earth rotates slightly more than 360 degrees in 24 hours. It completes a full rotation in roughly 23 hours, 56 minutes, and 4 seconds. However, since the Earth is also orbiting the sun, it needs to rotate a bit more for the sun to be overhead again. You can read the Wikipedia pages of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sidereal_time" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sidereal day</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synodic_day" target="_blank" rel="noopener">synodic day</a> for more information. Since we are interested in the time at which local noon occurs, we will consider synodic period.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>You can find when local noon occurs at your place on any day of the year at <a href="http://www.solar-noon.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">http://www.solar-noon.com/</a>.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></description></item><item><title>Research Seminars</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/research-seminars/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Feb 2022 02:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/research-seminars/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>Most research talks are being held online post lockdown, and as a result, one can access talks from all over the world.
I came across a website that lists upcoming research seminars and makes it easier to discover interesting talks.</p>
<p><a href="https://researchseminars.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://researchseminars.org/</a></p>
<p>This website was launched in April 2020 shortly after lockdown began.
It lists upcoming talks and seminars held in universities all over the world.
You can filter talks by topic, language, institution, and more.</p>

<figure >
    
    
    
    
    
    <picture>
        
        <img src="https://pranshugaba.com/articles/research-seminars/research-seminars.png" alt="Screenshot of the homepage of researchseminars.org">
    </picture>
    
    
    <figcaption>
        
            Screenshot of the homepage of researchseminars.org
            
            
            
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>


<p>For each talk, the site shows details such as the title, abstract, speaker, the targeted audience, and a link to the seminar&rsquo;s website.
Most talks have a livestream link available (either interactive like Zoom / Google Meet / Microsoft Teams or viewing only such as Youtube).
Links for some talks are not be available unless you register on this site.</p>
<p>Try to attend and participate in talks that pique your interest. The feeling of being able to attend a talk held halfway across the world is unmatched.</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>Advent Puzzles 2021</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/advent-puzzles-2021/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 05:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/advent-puzzles-2021/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>December is here, which means it&rsquo;s problem solving season!</p>
<h2 id="maths">Maths</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.mscroggs.co.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Matthew Scroggs</a> has posted the seventh edition of the <a href="https://www.mscroggs.co.uk/blog/91" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Advent calendar of maths puzzles</a> on his blog. A new puzzle is unlocked everyday, and you have until the end of the year to submit the answers. The first twenty-four puzzles each have a three digit solutions, and these solutions form the clues required to solve the main puzzle on the 25th.
Ten people who solve all puzzles correctly are randomly selected to win a T-shirt!</p>
<p>The problems are mostly from number theory and combinatorics, which are coincidentally two of my favourite areas of mathematics. I believe most people would find the problems interesting and challenging. I have solved the last three editions of this advent, and plan to solve it this year as well.</p>
<h2 id="programming">Programming</h2>
<p>This year, we get the seventh <a href="https://adventofcode.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Advent of Code</a> by <a href="http://was.tl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Eric Wastl</a>. Two programming puzzles are unlocked every day.
Solving these puzzles requires basic programming skills, but more importantly, critical thinking skills.
You are free to use any programming language to solve them. You can even use pen and paper, although I would not recommend it.
I recently started learning the functional programming language Haskell, and I am using it to solve these puzzles. I am loving the experience so far.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you know any other puzzles happening in December (or any other time of the year really), <a href="https://pranshugaba.com/contact/">let me know</a>!</p>
]]></description></item><item><title>The Tale of Despereaux</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/the-tale-of-despereaux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2015 17:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/articles/the-tale-of-despereaux/</guid><description><![CDATA[


<aside class="admonition info">
    <div class="admonition__title">
        Info
    </div>
	<div class="admonition__content">
        <p>Full Name: The Tale of Desperaux being a story of a mouse, a princess, some soup, and a spool of thread.<br>
Author: Kate DiCamillo<br>
Illustrated by: Timothy Basil Ering</p>

    </div>
</aside>
<p>The Tale of Despereaux is an excellent book. The characters are adorable and very well developed. However, the ending seems to be very abrupt.</p>
<p>This story is set in a world where mice and rats can speak. It is wonderful to listen to what these animals have to say. Their behavior is portrayed very similar to human behavior. And just like humans, there are heroes and villains among mice and rats, who will go against the wind, do something incredible; because they want to do it, and are not influenced by what others say.</p>
<p>The writer frequently talks to the reader, often at the end of each chapter, making it more enticing to read ahead.</p>
<p>The book consists of four parts, the author calls it 4 books. In the first three books, the author introduces three main characters. Their history is well narrated, in quite detail. The story jumps forward and backward in time very often. This is not difficult to follow and adds to the narrative. The time jumps make it more interesting.  In the fourth book the three characters meet and have nice interactions. I felt that the ending was very short, not very detailed. It is sad because the reader wants to read more about these lovable characters. But then again, I understand that writing an ending is always the toughest part.</p>
<p>The book does have a lot of humorous moments, exaggeration that is totally unlikely and also slightly dark humor.</p>
<p>Overall, it was a very nice experience. I would rate it 7/10</p>



<aside class="admonition more-info">
    <div class="admonition__title">
        More info
    </div>
	<div class="admonition__content">
        <p>ISBN: 9708744598698<br>
Number of Pages: 270<br>
Publisher: Walker Books and subsidiaries<br>
Published: 2004<br>
Language: English<br>
Illustrations: Yes<br>
Ages: 9-12</p>

    </div>
</aside>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>