<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Stories by Pranshu Gaba</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/stories/</link><description>Gripping tales of awe and wonder</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</managingEditor><webMaster>pranshu@pranshugaba.com (Pranshu Gaba)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2022 10:19:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://pranshugaba.com/stories/icon.png</url></image><atom:link href="https://pranshugaba.com/stories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Errand</title><link>https://pranshugaba.com/stories/the-errand/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 10:05:26 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://pranshugaba.com/stories/the-errand/</guid><description>
<![CDATA[<p>It was a dark and stormy knight. This was to his benefit, as his black armor helped him remain unspotted in the woods. Even the blazing midnoon sunlight could not cut through the dense canopy, leaving him well hidden in the dimly lit forest.</p>
<p>The knight lay prone amidst the dead leaves and branches, his satchel clutched close to his chest and his ear pressed to the ground. He waited till he was certain that the danger had passed, and then he waited some more. He finally got up and took a good look around.</p>
<p>The knight searched for clues that would help him find his destination, mayhaps a familiar tree or a rock formation, but found none. Although the woods were familiar to him &mdash; he had crossed them way more times than he cared for &mdash; he did not where he was. He had lost his bearings after the long and arduous chase. While he had managed to lose his followers, but he lost himself too.</p>
<p>The knight guessed he still had a long way to go, so he took a step in the direction that he thought would get him home.</p>
<hr>
<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>
]]></description></item></channel></rss>